<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A patterne of Popish peace. Or A peace of Papists with Protestants Beginning in articles, leagues, oathes, and a marriage. And ending in a bloudy massacre of many thousand Protestants.</title>
            <author>Hotman, François, 1524-1590.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 202KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 96 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44590</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831754</idno>
  <idno type="VID">36221</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248501647</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2910A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220350</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831754</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99831754e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44590)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36221)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2126:37)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A patterne of Popish peace. Or A peace of Papists with Protestants Beginning in articles, leagues, oathes, and a marriage. And ending in a bloudy massacre of many thousand Protestants.</title>
                  <author>Hotman, François, 1524-1590.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 184, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by L.N. for Richard Whitaker, and are to be sold at his shop in Paul's Church-yard at the signe of the Kings Armes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By François Hotman.</note>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 1 reads: A declaration of the furious outrages of France, with the slaughter of the admirall.</note>
                  <note>Caption title reads: A French massacre, a patterne of popish peace.</note>
                  <note>Errata at foot of p. 184.</note>
                  <note>Final leaf bears order to print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary, New York, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Catholics --  England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Protestants --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36221:1"/>
            <p>A PATTERNE OF POPISH PEACE. OR A Peace of Papists with Protestants.</p>
            <p>BEGINNING IN AR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, Leagues, Oathes, and a Marriage.</p>
            <p>And ending in a bloudy Mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sacre of many thousand <hi>Protestants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON. Printed by <hi>L. N.</hi> for RICHARD WHITAKER, and are to be sold at his shop in <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-yard at the signe of the Kings Armes. 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:36221:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36221:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader, that is wise already, or that he may be wise.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>SKE and enquire what are the things of highest, most solemne, and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Obligation, that may call for trust in the way of peace betweene the sons of men, and when you have found them, then have you found those very things, of which Papists, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pishly affected do make nets and snares to deceive Trust; and to destroy those that trust them; Be they <hi>Treaties, Leagues, Oathes, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:36221:3"/>These, even these sacred bonds of a secure peace, are those that are turned into <hi>cords</hi> and <hi>fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> to bind those that trust them to an <hi>assured ruine</hi> and <hi>Destruction.</hi> So they are not safe, because in their nature they draw Trust, but because they draw trust, they are dangerous, for by that Trust they doe deceive. Then by what <hi>Security</hi> can any be assured of any <hi>Peace</hi> with <hi>Papists,</hi> when the very <hi>Security</hi> doth <hi>Deceit,</hi> and <hi>Destroy?</hi> Beleeve it therefore, that nothing under heaven but <hi>Power,</hi> can make you safe from Papists: For if they gaine <hi>Trust</hi> from you, and you leave <hi>Power</hi> to them; you may see
<pb facs="tcp:36221:3"/>in the Papists of Ireland, what their fellowes would do in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; when they had nothing to complain of, but too much liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for an <hi>Idolatrous Religion;</hi> yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all having too much <hi>Power,</hi> they took advantage of that <hi>Power</hi> for an <hi>Irish Massacre</hi> of English <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants.</hi> Surely now in all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes which this Crown carries in the Title of it, the <hi>Popish plot</hi> of warre and murder hath had blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy passage, <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> But let not us become <hi>Nurses</hi> to such a <hi>Crimson brat,</hi> by gaining it the <hi>white milke</hi> of a <hi>weake</hi> and <hi>simple Peace.</hi> But where <hi>Trnst</hi> without <hi>Power</hi> would betray and
<pb facs="tcp:36221:4"/>destroy us, there let <hi>Power</hi> without any <hi>Trust</hi> (below that wherby the highest above will strengthen our <hi>Power</hi>) secure us. And to keepe us close to this Rule; let the <hi>patterne</hi> of this <hi>Peace,</hi> made by <hi>French popery,</hi> stand like a <hi>Pyramide</hi> before our eyes: And when you <hi>see</hi> it, <hi>heare</hi> it it also; for it <hi>speaks,</hi> and that which it speakes is this, <hi>Pray</hi> and <hi>provide;</hi> That the peace of <hi>French popery</hi> be not translated into <hi>English,</hi> by Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish <hi>Protestants.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>The end of the Epistle.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36221:4"/>
            <head>A Declaration of the furious outrages of <hi>France,</hi> with the slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>of the Admirall.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T were to be wished that the memory of the fresh slaughters, and of that butcherly murthering that hath lately been committed in a manner in all the townes of France, were utterly put out of the minds of men: for so much dishonour, and so great infamie hath thereby stain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the whole French Nation, that the most part of them are now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shamed of their own countrey, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed with two most filthy spots, <hi>falshood</hi> and <hi>cruelty.</hi> Of the which, whether hath been the greater, it is hard to say. But for asmuch as there flie every where abroad Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:36221:5"/>written by flatterers of the Court, and men corruptly hired for reward, which do most shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully set out things fained and fals<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imagined, in stead of truth, I thought my selfe bound to do this service to posterity, to put the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in writing as it was truly done indeed, being well inabled to have knowledge thereof, both by mine owne calamity, and by those that with their owne eyes beheld a great part of the same slaughters.</p>
            <p>In the yeare of our Lord 1561. when there seemed to be some pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill of troubles to arise by reason of the multitude of such as embraced the <hi>Religion</hi> (which they call <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed</hi>) for before that time the usuall manner of punishing such as durst professe that Religion, was besides losse and forfeiture of all their goods to the Kings use, to burne their bodies, at the request of the great Lords and Nobility, there was holden an assembly of the Estates in the Kings house at Saint
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:36221:5"/>Germains in Lay, neare to the City of Paris, at which Assembly, in presence, and with the Royall as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, of King <hi>Charles</hi> the ninth,
<note place="margin">A decree for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise of Religion in publike meetings, whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a cruell Massacre.</note> it was decreed, that from thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth it should not be prejudiciall to any man to professe the said Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and that it should be lawfull for them to have publike meetings and preachings for the exercise thereof, but in the Suburbs of Townes only.</p>
            <p>At this Assembly <hi>Francis</hi> Duke of Guise, being descended of the House of Loraine, and at that time Grand Master of the Kings House<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, was not present. But when he was enformed of this Decree, he boyled with incredible sorrow and anger, and within few dayes after at a little Towne in Champagne called Vassey, while the Professors of the said Religion were there at a Sermon, he, accompanied with a band of souldiers, set upon them, and slew men and women to the number of two hundred.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:36221:6"/>
            <p>There was among these of the religion (for so hereafter according to the usuall phrase of the French tongue wee intend to call them) <hi>Lewis</hi> of Burbon of the bloud Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, commonly called Prince of Conde, after the name of a certaine Towne, a man of great power by reason of his kindred to the King. Therefore when the Duke of Guise most vehemently strived against that law, and as much as in him lay, did utterly overthrow it, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled the common quiet thereby stablished, <hi>Gasper de Coligni</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall of France, and <hi>Francis de Andelot</hi> his brother, Captain of the Fantary, and other Princes, Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Gentlemen of the same Religion, come daily by heapes to the Prince of Conde, to complaine of the outragious boldnesse and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperate violence of the Duke of Guise.</p>
            <p>At that time <hi>Katherine de Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices,</hi> Pope <hi>Clements</hi> brothers daughter, and mother of King
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36221:6"/>
               <hi>Charles,</hi> borne in Florence a Citie of Italie, had the governance of the Realme in the Kings minority. For though by the law of France, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the inheritance nor the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistration of the Realme is granted to women, yet through the coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly negligence of <hi>Anthony</hi> King of Navarre, the said <hi>Katherine de Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices</hi> the Kings mother, aganst the custome of the realme, was joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with him in that office of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectorship.</hi> She fearing the presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and fierce pride of the Guisans,
<note place="margin">The Qu. mothers Letters to the Prince of Conde.</note> wrote to the Prince of Conde with her owne hand: which letters are yet remaining, and at the assemblie of the Princes of Germany at Franckford, holden under <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nand</hi> the Emperour, were produced and openly read about ten yeares past: wherin she earnestly besought him in so great hardnesse and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tresse not to for sake her, but to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count both the mother and the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, that is, both her selfe and the King, and the Kings brethren,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36221:7"/>committed to his faith and naturall kindnesse, and that he should with all speede, provide for their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon safety: assuring him, that she would so imprint in the Kings mind his travell in that behalfe, that he should never be loser by it.</p>
            <p>Within few dayes after the Duke of Guise wel-knowing how great authority the name of the King would carry in France,
<note place="margin">The poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the Duke of Guise to get the King into his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that he might the better effect his wicked en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprizes.</note> and to the intent that he would not seeme to attempt any thing rather of his own head than by the privity of the king, and having attained fit partners to joyn with him in these enterprises, he got the King into his power. Which thing being known abroad, and many hard encombrances ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon suddenly rising, and a great part of the nobility of France mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellously troubled with it, the Prince of Conde by advise of his friends, thought it best for him to take certaine townes and furnish them with garrisons: which was the beginning of the first civill war.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36221:7"/>For the Prince of Conde alleaged the cause of his taking armes,
<note place="margin">The be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ginning and cause of the first Civil war.</note> to be the defence of the Kings Edict, wherein consisted the safety of the common weale, and that it could not be repealed without most as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured undoing of the nation of France, and destruction of the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, by reason of the exceeding great multitude of those that daily joyned themselves to that <hi>Religion:</hi> Of which number such as being of noble birth, or were in power, dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, wealth, and credit above the rest, thought it not meet for them to suffer the punishments and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties accustomed to be extended on the professors thereof; beside that, they held themselves discontented that the Duke of Guise one newly come, a stranger, translated from the forrests of Loraine into France, would take upon him in France so great courage and so high domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and power. Therto was added the Queene mothers singular care (as was reported) for conservation
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36221:8"/>of peace and repressing the rage of the Guisians. Upon which opinion it is certian that above twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand men having regard onely to the Queenes inclination, joyned themselves to the side of those of the Religion, and to the defence of their profession, which at that time had besiged the force of the Kings power.</p>
            <p>After certaine battailes and many losses on both parts,
<note place="margin">The Duke of Guise slaine, whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a peace concluded, with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of free exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. The inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries done to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants by the Papists continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the Peace.</note> and the Duke of Guise slain, within a yeare, peace was made with this condition, that they of the Religion should have free liberty thereof, and should have assemblies and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings for the exercise of the same in certaine places.</p>
            <p>This peace continued in force, but not in all places, during five yeares: for in the most townes and jurisdictions, the Officers that were affectionate to the Romish side, whom they commonly call Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, did all the displeasures they could to those of the Religion.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36221:8"/>Therefore, when <hi>Ferdizando Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vares de Toledo,</hi> commony called Duke of Alva, was leading an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie not farre from the frontiers of France, against those of the low countrey which embraced the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion,
<note place="margin">The Qu. mother obtains an armie of Switzers under a false pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of defence, to oppresse the Prince of Conde, &amp; the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall, and the other Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants.</note> against the will of the King of Spaine, the Queene mother caused to be levied and brought in to France sixe thousand Switzers for a defence (as she caus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to be bruted) but as the successe hath proved, for this intent, that the Prince of Conde, the Admirall and other noble men of the Religion, if they escaped the treason prepared for them, and listed to defend them selves by force, and trie it by battell, might be suddenly oppressed ere they were provided. For the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> then had the managing of these matters, did not at that time well trust the souldiers of France. Many things pertaining to the course of that time, and the renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the warre, must here for hast to our present purpose be necessari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly omitted.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:36221:9"/>
            <p>When the warre had endured about sixe months, peace was made with the same conditions that we have above rehearsed, that all men should have free libertie to follow and professe the Religion reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. For this was ever one and the last condition upon all the warres. But within few dayes or months after,
<note place="margin">The trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery of the Peace.</note> it was plainly vnderstood, that the same peace was full of guile and treason, and finaly, that it was no peace, but most cruell war cloaked under the name of peace. For forthwith all those townes which they of the Religion had yelded up, were possessed and strengthened with garrisons of souldiers of the contrary side, sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving one Towne on the sea-coast in the parts of Xantoigne commonly called Rochell. For the men of that towne about two hundred yeares before, had yelded themselves to the Kings power and allegiance, with this cōdition, that they should never be constrained against their
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36221:9"/>will to receive any garrison soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers.</p>
            <p>Also the Princes of Conde and the Admirall were advertised;
<note place="margin">Advertise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of treason a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Prince of Conde, &amp; the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, by <hi>Tavaignes</hi> made Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shall of France hereupon.</note> that there was treason againe prepared to intrap them by Tavaignes, a mā given to murther and mischiefe, which had lately been made Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shall of France, and that if they did not speedely avoyde the same, it should shortly come to passe, that they should be deceived and taken by him, and delivered up to the crueltie of their adversaries.</p>
            <p>Upon the receit of these advertis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, they immediatly make hast to Rochell, carying with them their wives and young children,
<note place="margin">The be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of a third ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill warre</note> which was the beginning of the third civill warre, the most sharpe and miserable of all the rest.</p>
            <p>There was at that time in the Court, <hi>Charles</hi> Cardinall of Lorain, brother to the Duke of Guise, which (as is above said,) was slayne in the first war, one accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted most subtill and craftie of all
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36221:10"/>the rest, but of a terrible, cruell and troublesome disposition, and thought intollerable even at Rome it selfe. This man, they of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion reported to be the most sharpe and hatefull enemy of their profession, and him they abhorred above all other for the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty of his nature, and named him the <hi>firebrand</hi> of all civill flames. He at the beginning of the third civill war,
<note place="margin">Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the Kings former E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts by the perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of <hi>Charles</hi> Cardinall of Lorain, he publish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, that no man professe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on but the Romish.</note> perswaded the King to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish an Edict, that no man professe any Religion but the Romish or Popish, and that whosoever should imbrace any other, should be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted as traytours. In that same Edict Printed at Paris, this sentence was expressely conteynd, and for the strangenesse of the matter, and for that it stained the Kings name with the most dishonorable spot of perjurie and breach of faith, it was in other impressions afterward o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. And it was further then declared, that albeit the King had in many Edictes before that time
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36221:10"/>permitted the freedome of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet his meaning ever was to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and cause to be retained of all men, the onely Romish or popish Religion within his Realme.</p>
            <p>After many overthrowes on both partes given and received, whereas the end of this third warre was thought likely to be the harder, by reason of the breach of faith in the yeares before, and on the other side the state of the Realme by reason of the waste that the Cities were brought unto, and extreme pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the meane people and hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen, did require some treatie of composition, the King sent mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sengers to the Admirall,
<note place="margin">Civill Peace pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded upon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of joyning against a forraigne enemy.</note> to signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie unto him in the Kings name, that the King himselfe had at length found out a most sure way of peace and concord, namely that the armies of both partes joyned together, should goe into the low countrey against the Duke of Alva which had been the author of the late calamities in France. He signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:36221:11"/>further, that he had great causes of quarrels against the King of Spayne, and this principally, that he had invaded and held by force, an Island of the newfound Land called Florida, which had been ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the French, and kept under his dominion, suddenly slaying all the souldiers there: &amp; likewise the Marquesdome of Finall, the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants wherof had but a little time be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore, yeelded thēselves to the Kings subjection and allegeance. He said that the most stedfast band of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord should be that forren war, and that there could no other better meane be devised to drowne the memory of the former dissentions in eternall forgetfulnesse.</p>
            <p>To the performance hereof, he said it was a matter of most apt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, that <hi>Lodovick</hi> Count of Nassaw, brother to to the Prince of Aurenge, had been now two yeers in the Admiralls camp, to whome the Admirall gave principall credit in all things, and that by him and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36221:11"/>his fellowes of the low country, &amp; others whom he understood to fav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our his part, it might easily bee brought to passe that certaine Cities might be surprised. and thereby great advantage be attained to the atchieving of the war.</p>
            <p>The Admirall hearing these things was marvellously troubled. For albeit he doubted not of the Kings fidelity, yet therwithall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things fell into his minde to be considered: as the power of the Cardinall and rest of the Guisians, who were well knowne to have been at all times most affectionate to the King of Spayne. For the Duke of Guise had left a sonne, a very yong man, called <hi>Henry,</hi> to whom the Queene had given all the offices and places of honor that his father had borne before, being unfit thereto by age, and against the ancient lawes and customes, and also through the traiterous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity of certaine of the Kings counsell, whom she knew for their
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36221:12"/>affection to Popish Religion, to be most addicted to the Spanish King and that divers of them had great yeerely pensions of him, and did disclose unto him the affaires of the Realme.
<note place="margin">The Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals snares in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking of this war.</note> He remembred how here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it came to passe, that the same Kings Embassador (which among strange nations seemed vtterly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible) was admitted into the privie Counsell of France, and that one <hi>Biragio</hi> a Lumbard, and (as it is reported) a traytour to his owne countrey, otherwise alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether vnlearned, and specially ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the civill Law, was yet for the subtilty of his wit advanced to so great honour, that he executed the Chancellours office, <hi>Michael Hospitall</hi> being displaced, a man knowne to be such a one, as there was not in all degrees of men any either more wise, or more learned, or more zelously loving his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. Here withall he considered the slanderous cavillations of his adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries, to whom hereby might seem
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:36221:12"/>an occasion given, as if the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall were of a troublesome nature, and could not abide any quietnesse, nor could long rest at home with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out some tumultuous stir. Hereunto the messiengers replyed as they were able, and therewithall allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged this cause of so sodaine hatred against the Spanish King, that one <hi>Albenie</hi> late returned out of Spaine, had informed the King and the Queene mother for certainty, that King <hi>Philip</hi> a few moneths before, had poysoned his wife the French Kings sister, and had spred rumors of her thoroughout all Spaine, such as for the honour of many persons are meet not to be disclosed. But nothing moved the Admirall so much as the cheerful earnestness of <hi>Lodovick</hi> of Nassaw, who as soone as he was advertised of that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose of the King, omitted nothing that he thought might serve to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the Admirall thereunto.</p>
            <p>The Admirall perswaded hereby nothing fearing the infidelity of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36221:13"/>those of the Court,
<note place="margin">The Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall not fearing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity, harkens to a composi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Peace con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of liberty to use the Religion.</note> gave his mind to harken to composition. And so was the third civill warre ended, and the peace concluded with the same conditions that were before, that every man should have free liberty to use and professe the Religion.</p>
            <p>Within few monthes after this, divers Princes of Germany, that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured the Religion reformed, and among those the three Electors, the Palsgrave, the Duke of Saxony, and the Marquesse of Brandeburge, sent their Embassadours into France to the King, to gratulate vnto him for the new reconciliation of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. And because they accompted it greatly to behove them selves that the same concord should re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine stedfast and of long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, they promised, that if any would for that cause procure trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or make war upon him either within his owne dominions, or without, they and their followers should be ready to defend him. To this Embassage the King first by
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:36221:13"/>words,
<note place="margin">The Kings subscripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and faith gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credly to observe the pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note> and afterward by a booke subscribed with his own hand, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered and gave his faith, that he would for ever most sacredly and faithfully observe his Edict of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cification.</p>
            <p>Hereby so much the more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly the Admirall suffered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to be drawn to the said purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses for the Low-countrey, although oftentimes calling to mind the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Queen mother, he used to say to divers, and specially to <hi>Theligny,</hi> to whom he afterward maried his daughter, that he great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly suspected the rolling wit of that woman. For (said he) so soone as she hath brought us into that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration against the Low-countrey, she will leave us in the midst.</p>
            <p>Neverthelesse, the Count of Nassaw writeth to his brother, and they conferring their advises toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, send messengers to the King, that if it please him to deale with the matter of the Low-countrey, they will shortly so doe, that hee
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:36221:14"/>shall by their many and great ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, well perceive their affection and devotion toward him. The King writeth againe to them in most loving termes, saying that their Message most highly pleased him, and he gave to them both his hearty thanks.</p>
            <p>About the same time Maximilian the Emperour pitying the estate of the Prince of Aurenge (as he said) treated by his Embassadours with the King of Spaine, and had in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner obtained, that the Prince should have all his goods restored unto him, but with this condition, that he should have no house within the territory of the low countrie, but settling his residence and dwelling elsewhere, he should freely enjoy all his revenewes. Which matter being reported to the French King, he immediatly sent messengers to the Prince of Aurenge willing him to looke for nothing by that dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Emperour, saying that it was but a fraud and guileful device
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:36221:14"/>intended for this purpose, onely to breake up his levying of souldiers that he had begun in Germanie: and assuring him, that if he would cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit and follow him, hee would give him aid sufficient to recover his estate.</p>
            <p>The Prince of Aurenge perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by these promises of King <hi>Charles,</hi> continued his musters, and determined a while to bear the charges though they were heavy to him, while such things as were necessary for the warre, were in preparing. In the meane time <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dovick</hi> in disguised apparel went to Paris to the King. Forasmuch as the season of the yeare by this time seemed not commodious to levy an armie, for the winter was at hand, by assent they deferred the matter till the next summer.</p>
            <p>These things thus hanging, the Prince of Aurenge his captaines by sea, did oftentimes set upon the Spanyards and Portugals, and such ships as they took they brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:36221:15"/>the haven of Rochell, which then was in the power of the Prince of Condees part: and there they openly vttered and sould their prizes to the men of the towne and other merchants of France, whereupon the Embassadour of Spaine made often complaints to the Kings privy councell.</p>
            <p>And forasmuch as they thought it very avaylable to this enterprise, that <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Queene of England might be brought into league with them, the King commited the dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in that matter to the Admirall. For,
<note place="margin">The Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirals ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at the Court.</note> a few moneths before, the King had with most sweet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luring letters, gotten him to the Court, where he was most hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably entertained: and to take from him all occasion of distrust upon his adversaries, or of otherwise sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting of the Kings or Queene mothers affection towards him, first, all the Guisians of a set purpose departed the Court then the King gave the Admirall free liberty to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:36221:15"/>take with him what company and what furniture he would: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it was thought that he had more confidence in the Marshall Cosse, then in the rest, therefore the King commanded the said Marshall to be ever at hand with the Admirall, and to assist him in the Kings name if any need were.</p>
            <p>The matter of the league with England, the Admiral so diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and industriously handled, that within short space after by Embas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sadours sent,
<note place="margin">The League with Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnely confirmed. And the first and chiefest condition, liberty of Religion and the observati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Edict of Pacifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> and by faith given and received, and oathes solemnly taken on both parts, it was confirmed. Concerning the procurement of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther leagues and amities, such as might seem to further the enterprise of the low country, the Admirall also travelled in the Kings name, and by his commandement, and had in a manner brought all these things to an end. And of all those leagues, the first and principall condition was, that the liberty of Religion should continue, and that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:36221:16"/>the King should most diligently and sincerely observe this Edict of pacification.</p>
            <p>Though these things seemed to be handled secretly, yet by the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters both of <hi>Biragio</hi> the Vicechan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, of whom we made menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before, and of <hi>Morvilliers</hi> whem for his hypocriticall leane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, children commonly called the <hi>Chimera</hi> or Bugge of the Court, and by advertisements of Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>de Pelve,</hi> a man most fit either to invent or execute any treason, they were carried to the Bishop of Rome,
<note place="margin">The Popes Embassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor to the King of France, with his Embas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage.</note> who by advise of his Cardinals sent by &amp; by one of their number, called <hi>Alexandrine,</hi> in the midst of most sharp winter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to France, with these instructions, to perswade the King to enter into the society of the league of Trent, whereof the first and principall ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle was, that the confederats should joyne their powers and make war upon the Turks and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes, meaning by the name of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:36221:16"/>Heretikes, all those Princes that did permit the vse of the reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion within their dominions.</p>
            <p>The Cardinall <hi>Alexandrine</hi> was honourably received in the court, but yet dismissed without atchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his purpose. For so was it bruited among the people, and commonly beleeved through-out France: albeit he himselfe secretly seemed to returne very merry and cheerfull to the Pope: and as it is reported, did sometime say that he received such answer of the King as was not to be published, and that the King and Queene mother had largely satisfied him.</p>
            <p>Forasmuch as it was thought a matter greatly avayling to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprise of the low countrey, to send certaine ships into the English Seas that if any aid should be sent into the low countrey to the Duke of Alva out of Spaine, it might so be stopped, <hi>Strozza</hi> and the Baron <hi>de la Guard</hi> were appointed for that purpose, to whom the King gave
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36221:17"/>in commandement to rigge forth certaine ships of Burdeaux and Rochell, well armed and well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted, and to provide with all speede all things needfull for those ships. The Ambassadour of Spayne somewhat moved with this prepar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, made divers complaints to the Kings counsell on the behalfe of the King his master, and yet never received any other answer, but that the King thought it not likely, and that he would send Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners to Burdeaux and to Rochel, with letters and commandement that there should be no preparation made to the sea, and if any had been made, it should be enquired of. what instructions were secretly and closely underhand given to these two captaines of that navie, we do not certainely know. But this no man can doubt of, but that they had commission to seize upon all ships wherein any Spanish souldiers should be transported into the low-countrey, and that all this prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:36221:17"/>to the sea, was ordained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Spanish King and the Duke of Alva.</p>
            <p>And moreover that the Admiral at the same time received comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement from the King, to send es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pials into Peru, an Island of the new found world, most plentiful of gold above all the other, now-being in the Spanyards dominion, to learne, if there were any good enterprise to be attempted or atchived for the getting of it. Which matter was committed to a certaine gentleman, one of the Admirals trayne, who went thither accompanyed with a certaine Portingal, a man most skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of those Navigations, whom the Admirall had joyned with him by the Kings commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Now it can not be expressed how many and how great tokens of a most loving minde the King at that time shewed to the Admiral, and to the County <hi>Rochfoucault,</hi> and to <hi>Theligny,</hi> and to the rest of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:36221:18"/>chiefe Noble-men of the <hi>Religion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Many most speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous tokens of the Kings love to the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall.</note> First, all such things as in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer warres had been taken away in the Townes, Fermes and Castels of the Admirall and <hi>d' Andelot,</hi> the King caused to be sought out and restored. If there were any other whom the King understood to be beloved and esteemed of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall, or to have attained any spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall honour in the said late warres, those he liberally benefited and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded. To the Admirall himselfe he commanded one day to be given an hundred thousand pounds of his own treasure in recompence of his former losses. When his brother the Cardinall <hi>Chastillion,</hi> endowed with many great and wealthy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices,
<note place="margin">The King writes to the Duke of Savoy for savour to be shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi>
               </note> was departed this life, the King gave him the fruits of one whole yeare. Also the King wrote to <hi>Philibert</hi> Duke of Savoy, that he should doe him a most ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable pleasure, if he did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deale more gently with those that in the former wars had ayded
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:36221:18"/>those of the <hi>Religion,</hi> but also would use clemencie and milde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse toward all other that profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the same <hi>Religion</hi> within his dominions.</p>
            <p>And for that there was old en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity betweene the Guisans and the Admirall, whereby it was to be doubted that perillous contentions would arise in the Realme of France,
<note place="margin">The Kings reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Guisans and the Admirall.</note> The King willed it to be sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified to them both in his name, that they should for his sake and the Common-weales, give over those displeasures, and hee prescribed them a certain forme of reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and agreement, the same wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the foundations had been laid al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most six years before in the Towne of Molins, where the King calling to him the greatest Estates of the Realme after consultation and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation had upon the matter, pronounced the Admirall not guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the death of the Duke of Guise, wherewith he was charged by the young Duke of Guise and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:36221:19"/>his kinsmen: and so the King by the advise of his Counsel had ended that controversie.</p>
            <p>Furrhermore,
<note place="margin">Cardinall <hi>Loraines</hi> departure to Rome, and C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall <hi>Pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey,</hi> under pretence of choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing a new Pope.</note> the Cardinall of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine (who as we have sayd was the very forger of all the former warres) to take away all jelousie of new practises, was departed to Rome, and took with him his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar friend the late created Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>Pelvey,</hi> one reputed a most subtil and crafty person, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of going to the election of a new Pope in place of the old Pope then lately deceassed.</p>
            <p>But there was none greater and more assured token of publique peace and quietnesse then this,
<note place="margin">A further confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Peace un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of marriage of the kings sister to Prince <hi>Henry,</hi> son to the Queene of Navarre.</note> that the King purposed to give his sister <hi>Margaret</hi> in marriage to the Prince <hi>Henry</hi> the sonne of the Queene of Navarre, which Prince had in the last warre defended the cause of the Religion, and been soveraigne of their armie. Which marriage the King declared, that it should be the most streight bond of civill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:36221:19"/>and the most assured testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of his good will to those of the Religion.</p>
            <p>Yea, and also because it was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged, that the said Prince <hi>Henry</hi> was restrained in conscience, so as he might not marry the Lady <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graet,</hi> being of a contrary Religion, a Catholike and given to the rites of the Romish Church, the King for answer said that he would dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge her of the Popes lawes, and notwithstanding the crying out of all his courtiers to the contrary, he permitted him, that without all ceremonies, in the porch of the great Church of Paris, the marriage should be celebrated in such a forme as the ministers of the reformed Church misliked not.</p>
            <p>Which thing being by report and letters spread through the world, it cannot be expressed how much it made the hearts of those of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion assured and out of care, and how it cast out all feare and jelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies out of their minds, what a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:36221:20"/>confidence it brought them of the Kings good will toward them. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, how much it rejoyced for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren Princes and States that favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the same <hi>Religion?</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral more fully esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished by the Kings Letter with his owne hand and Seale.</note> But the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirals mind was much more sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished by a Letter which about the same time <hi>Theligny</hi> brought him with the Kings own hand and seal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, wherin was cōtained that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever the Admirall should doe for the matter of the intended war of the Low-country, the King would allow and ratifie the same, as done by his own commandement. About that time <hi>Lodovick</hi> of Nassaw with the Queen of Navarre, a Lady most zealously affected to the <hi>Religion,</hi> came to the French Court. The League was made betweene King <hi>Charles</hi> &amp; the Prince of Aurenge, and the Articles thereof put in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. The marriage was appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be holden in the City of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris. For which cause the Queene of Navarre during those few dayes repaired thither to provide things
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:36221:20"/>for the solemnitie of the wedding. For the same cause the King sent to the Admirall one <hi>Caivagnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Kings perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Admiral to go to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suring him of safety from all dangers.</note> a man of an excellent sharpe wit, whom for the Admirals sake the King had advanced to great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, requiring the Admirall to goe before to Paris, as well for the said preparation, as also for the matter of the warre of the Low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countries, promising that he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe would within few dayes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after him: assuring him that there was no cause for him to feare the threatnings and madde out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages of the Parisians. For, in as much as the same Towne is above all other given to superstition, and is with seditious preachings of Monkes and Friers daily enflamed to cruelty, it is hard to expresse how bitterly they hated the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and the professors of that <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi> Whereto was added a griefe of their mind conceived certaine dayes before, by reason of a certain stone-crosse gilt and built after the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:36221:21"/>manner of a spire steeple, common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called <hi>Gastignes</hi> Crosse, which the Admirall with great earnest suit obtained of the King to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrowne: for he alleaged, that being erected in the middest of the rage of the Civill warre, as it were in triumph to the reproach of one of the <hi>Religion,</hi> it was a monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of civill dissention, and so a matter offensive to peace and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord.</p>
            <p>The King wel knowing this dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hate of the Parisians to the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall,
<note place="margin">To take away all feare from the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, the King wrote Letters to <hi>Marcell</hi> to prevent all tumults, and so the Duke of Anjow and the Queen did the same.</note> wrote his Letters to <hi>Marcel</hi> the Provost of the Merchants (w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> is the highest dignity in Paris) with sharp threatnings if there should be raised any stirre or trouble by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the Admirals comming. To the same effect also the Duke of Anjow, the Kings brother, and the Queen mother, wrote to the same <hi>Marcel,</hi> and the rest of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates of Paris, so that now there seemed utterly no occasion left for the Admirall to feare or distrust.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:36221:21"/>And within few dayes after, the King sent <hi>Briquemault,</hi> a man of great vertue and estimation, to the Admirall, with the same instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, saying, that the matter of the Low-countrey could not well be dealt in without his presence.</p>
            <p>The Admirall perswaded by thus many meanes, and filled with good hope and courage, determined to go to Paris, where so soone as he was arrived and had been honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably and lovingly entertained of the King and his brethren, and the Queene mother, and consultation entred among them about the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for the Low-countrey, he declared to the King at large, how the Duke of Alva was in levying of great power, &amp; preparing an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and that if the King should dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble his purpose, it would come to passe that many thereby would shew themselves slower and slacker to the enterprise, and that now were offered great meanes to doe good, which if hee let slip, hee
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:36221:22"/>should not so easily recover the like againe hereafter. And therefore it was best to take the advantage of this opportunity.</p>
            <p>A few dayes before, <hi>Lodovick</hi> of Nassaw went secretly into the frontiers of the Low-countrey, and tooke with him as partners of his journey, and privy to his counsell, three French-men of great credit with the Admirall, namely, <hi>Sau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>court, la Nove,</hi> &amp; <hi>Genlis,</hi> to whom the King had given in charge to see if they could by any means attempt and possesse any Townes bordering upon his Realme. They gathering divers other Gentlemen into their company, went speedily into the Low-countrey, the Admirall not knowing of it. Who as soone as he understood of their going thither, wrote unto them that hee much marvelled what they meant, saying that he well knew there could be no power gotten ready before for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty dayes end, and that they should be well advised to do nothing rash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:36221:22"/>nor to overthrow with haste their devises that seemed not ripe to be executed.</p>
            <p>The Count of Nassaw enflamed with the sight and desire of his Countrey, and fearing the mutable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the King, did first at the sudden set upon Valentiennes, but being repulsed by the Spanish soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers that were in garrison in the Castell, hee hastily departed to Montz, and took the Towne, being a place very strong by nature, and well furnished with all things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary for the warre. Which thing being by report, and messengers spread abroad in the Low-country, and dispatched into France &amp; Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many, both encouraged all them of the <hi>Religion</hi> with great hope, and also seemed to have now plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and openly deciphered and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>closed the minde of the French King. Moreover, <hi>Genlis</hi> returning to Paris, when hee had made re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port to the King of all the matter as it had proceeded, easily obtained
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:36221:23"/>of him, that by his assent he might levie certaine bandes of foot-men and horsemen of France, and carrie them to succour Montz. But by the way when he was entred into the bounds of the Low-country, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving with him to the number of foure thousand foot-men, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout foure hundred horse-men, they were beset by the Duke of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va, and the most part of them di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stressed: which thing was well knowne to have been wrought by the meanes of the Guisians, which by daily messages and letters, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertised the Duke of Alva of their purposes and prenaration. Which false-hood of theirs, many most affectionat to the Romish <hi>Religion,</hi> were highly offended with, because a great number addicted to the same Romish <hi>Religion</hi> were in that company.</p>
            <p>With this losse, and with the rescue of the Towne of Valentien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, the King seemed to be much troubled, for he feared lest his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:36221:23"/>being disclosed to the Spanish King, would at length breede some cause of quarrel and war. Howbeit, when he began to remember, that a great part of his secrets was already revealed to the Duke of Alva, he oftentimes resolved to utter his mind plainly, and to make open war. But he was withdrawn from that purpose by certain men which the Admirall had long before con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, that they would so do. Howbeit he gave the Admirall liberty to send whatso ever he thought meet to further the Prince of Aurenge his enterprise, and as great supply either of foot-men or of hors-men as he could to the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie which the Prince of Aurenge had levied in Germanie. When the Admirall for that cause had made request that he might leavie thirty troopes of horsemen, and as many ensignes of footmen, he easily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained it.</p>
            <p>For the entertainement of these footmen it behooved to have mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:36221:24"/>wherefore at the request of the Admirall, the King called for his Treasurer and commanded him to deliver the Admirall so much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney as the Admirall should thinke meete, and charged him, that he should not in any wise after the usu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all manner of the accompts of fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, write the causes of the receit but only set it downe in this forme: This summe of money was paid to the Admiral such a day by the kings commandement, for certaine cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses which the King hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not to be written: and to this warrant the King subscribed with his owne hand.</p>
            <p>Also the King wrote to <hi>Mondu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet,</hi> his Embassadour in the Low-countrey, to travell as earnestly as he could, for their deliverance, that were taken at the overthrow of Genlis, which commandement it is said that <hi>Monducet</hi> did most faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and diligently execute.</p>
            <p>Not long before this, <hi>Ioane</hi> Queen of Navarre above mentioned,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:36221:24"/>died in the Court at Paris, of a sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den sicknesse, being about the age of forty and three yeares, where the suspition was great that she died of poyson, and her body was for that cause opened by the Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, there was no tokens of poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son espied. But shortly after, by the detectionof one A.P. it hath been found that she was poysoned with a venomed smell of a paire of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumed gloves,
<note place="margin">The Qu. of Navar poysoned by the Kings A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecary in Paris.</note> dressed by one <hi>Renat</hi> the Kings Apothecary an Italian, who had a shop at Paris upon Saint <hi>Michaels</hi> bridge, near unto the Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace: which could not be espied by the Physitions which did not open the head nor looked into the braine It is well knowne that the same man about certaine yeares past, for the same intent gave to <hi>Lewes</hi> Prince of Conde a poysoned Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander, which the Prince left with one <hi>le Grosse</hi> his Surgeon, who was by little and little poysoned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and so swelled, that he hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly escaped with his life.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:36221:25"/>
            <p>By her death, the Kingdom came to the Prince <hi>Henry</hi> her sonne, to whom, as is above-said, the Kings sister was promised and contracted.</p>
            <p>Things being, as it seemed, through-out all France in most peaceable estate, and the concord of all degrees well established, the day was appointed for the Marriage of the King of Navarre, which day, all they that fancied the <hi>Religion,</hi> estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med so much the more joyfull to them, because they saw the King wonderfully bent thereunto, and all good men judged the same a most assured pledge and stablish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of civill concord; whereas, on the contrary part, the Guisans and other enemies of common quietnesse greatly abhorred the same marriage.</p>
            <p>When the day came, the marriage was with royall pompe solemnized before the great Church of Paris, and a certaine forme of words so framed, as disagreed with the <hi>Religion</hi> of neither side, was by
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:36221:25"/>the Kings commandement pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by the Cardinall of Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon, the King of Navar's unkle:
<note place="margin">The so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity of the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of Prince <hi>Henry</hi> and the Kings sister, with great joy on both sides.</note> and so the matrimony was celebrated with great joy of the King and all good men, the Bride was with great train and pomp led into the Church to heare Masse, and in the meantime the Bridegroome, who misliked these Ceremonies, together with <hi>Henry</hi> Prince of Conde, sonne of <hi>Lewes,</hi> and the Admirall, and other Noble-men of the same <hi>Religion,</hi> walked without the Church-doore, waiting for the Brides returne.</p>
            <p>While these things were in doing at Paris, <hi>Strozzi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Souldiers sent often into the Towne, under colour of Buying things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary.</note> who as we have said, had the charge of the Kings power at sea, hovering upon the coast of Rochell, did now and then send of his Captaines and souldiers into the Town, under colour of buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things necessary: and sometime he came thither also himselfe. The like was done at the same time in another part of France, by the horse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of <hi>Gonzague</hi> Duke of Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:36221:26"/>neere to the Towne of <hi>la Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rité,</hi> which hath a bridge over the River of Loyre, and remained till that time in the power of those of the <hi>Religion,</hi> by reason of the great number of them there inhabiting. This troop was of those horse-men which the King hath accustomed to keepe in ordinary wages in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Country, whereof the most part were Italians, country-men to their Captain <hi>Lewes Gonzague,</hi> to whom the Queene mother had given the daughter and heire of the Duke of Nivers in marriage. They request<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the Townes-men,
<note place="margin">The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of Lions takes a view of all the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants, and writ them in a book, which was after cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the bloudy booke.</note> that they might make their Muster within the Towne, saying that they had received warrant from the King so to doe, and shewed the Kings Letters therefore. At Lions the Governour of the Town, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a view to be taken of all those that professed the <hi>Religion,</hi> and their names to be written in a book and brought unto him: which book shortly after, according to the suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:36221:26"/>was called the bloudy booke.</p>
            <p>After themarriage ended at Paris, which was the time that the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall had appointed to returne to his owne house, he moved the King concerning his departure. But so great was the preparatiō of Playes, so great was the magnificence of banquets and shewes, and the King so earnestly bent to those matters, that he had no leasure, not only for waighty affaires, but also not so much as to take his naturall sleepe. For in the French Court, Dancings, Maskings, Stage-playes (wherein the King exceedingly delighted) are commonly used in the night-time: and so the time that is fittest for counsel and matters of governance, is by reason of nightly riotous sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings up, of necessity consumed in sleepe. So great also is the familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of men and the women of the Queen mothers traine, and so great liberty of sporting, entertainment and talking together, as to forren Nations may seeme incredible, and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:36221:27"/>be thought of all honest persons a matter not very convenient for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of noble young Ladies chastitie. Moreover, if there come any pandor or bawde out of Italie, or any Scholemaster of shamefull and filthy lust, he winneth in short time marvellous favour and credit. And such a multitude is there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne to be of Italians, commonly throughout all France, specially in the court, since the administration of the Realme was commited to the Queene mother, that many doe commonly call it France-Italian, and some terme it a Colonie, and some a common sincke of Italie.</p>
            <p>These madnesses of the Court,
<note place="margin">The Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siring to depart from Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, but was stayed, partly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he could not have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse to the King, who was exces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sively in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ive on his sports and ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly because he was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated to stay and deliver Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions to the King in the cause of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons.</note> were the cause that the Admirall could not have accesse to the Kings speech, nor entrance to deale in waighty matters. But when they that were sent from the reformed Churches to complaine of injuries commonly done to those of the <hi>Religion,</hi> understood of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirals purpose to depart, they
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:36221:27"/>did with all speed deliver to him their bookes and petitions, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sought him, not to depart from the Court till he had dealt in the cause of the Churches, and delivered their petitions to the King and his Councell. For this cause the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall resolved to deferre his going for a while, till he might treat with the Kings Councell con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning those requests: for the King had promised him that he would shortly entend those matters, and be present with the Councel himselfe.</p>
            <p>Besides this delay, there was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other matter that stayed him. There was owing to the Rutters of <hi>Germanie,</hi> which had served on the part of the <hi>Religion</hi> in the last war, great summes of money for their wages, in which matter the Admirall travelled with incredible earnestnesse and care.</p>
            <p>Concerning all these affaires,
<note place="margin">The Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirals ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse to the King, and treats with him.</note> the Admiral (as he determined before) having accesse and opportunitie for that purpose, moved the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:36221:28"/>Kings privy Councell the 22. day of August, which was the fifth day after the King of Navar's marriage, and spent much time in that trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.
<note place="margin">The Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning home from the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, was treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously shot out at a window, and sorely wounded.</note> About noone, when he was in returning home from the Councell, with a great company of Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Gentlemen, behold, a Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quebuzier out of a window of a house neare adjoyning, shot the Admirall with two bullets of lead thorow both the armes. When the Admirall felt himselfe woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, nothing at all amazed, but with the same countenance that he was accustomed, he said, thorow yonder window it was done: go see who are in the house. What mā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of trechery is this? Then he sent a certain Gentleman of his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to the King to declare it unto him. The King at that time was playing at Tennise with the Duke of Guise.
<note place="margin">The King seemingly much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at the Admirals hurt.</note> As soone as he heard of the Admirals hurt, he was marvellously moved, as it seemed, and threw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his racket that he played with
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:36221:28"/>on the ground, and taking with him his brother in law, the King of Navarre, hee retired into his Castle.</p>
            <p>The Gentlemen that were with the Admirall brake into the house from whence he received his hurt, there they found only one woman, the keeper of the house, and short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after also a boy, his lackey that had done <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he deed, and therewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all they found the harquebuze lying upon the table in that chamber from whence the noyse was heard: him that shot they found not,
<note place="margin">Hee that shot the Admirall flyes, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving fresh horses rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> for he in great haste was runne away out at the back-gate, and getting on horse-back, which he had waiting for him ready sadled at the doore, he rode a great pace to Saint <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonies</hi> gate, where he had a fresh horse tarying for him, if need were, and another at <hi>Marcelles</hi> gate. Then by the kings commandement a great number rode out in poste into all parts to pursue him:
<note place="margin">The King sends posts after him.</note> but for that he was slipped into by-wayes,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:36221:29"/>and received into a certaine Castle, they could not overtake him.</p>
            <p>At the sute of the King of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varre,
<note place="margin">The King gives com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission to three of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of Paris to examine the bust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.</note> and the Prince of Conde and other, the King by and by gave commssion for enquirie to be made of the matter, and committed the examining thereof to three chosen persons of the Parliament of Paris, <hi>Thuan</hi> and <hi>Morsant</hi> and <hi>Viol</hi> a couuseller.</p>
            <p>First it was found that the same house belonged to a Priest, a Canon of Saint <hi>Germaine,</hi> whose name is <hi>Villemure,</hi> which had been the Duke of Guises schole-master in his youth,
<note place="margin">The busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined.</note> and still continued a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayner toward him. Then the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man which we said was found in the house, being taken and brought before them, confessed that a few dayes before, there came to her one <hi>Chally</hi> sometime a M<seg rend="sup">r.</seg>
               <hi>de Hostel</hi> of the Duke of Guises house, and now of the Kings court, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded her to make much of the man that had done this deede,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:36221:29"/>and to lodge him in the same bed and chamber where <hi>Villemure</hi> was wont to lie, for that he was his friend and very familiar acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and that <hi>Villemure</hi> would be very glad of it. The name of him that shot was very diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kept secret. Some say it was <hi>Manrevet,</hi> which in the third ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill warre traiterously slew his cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Monsieur de Movy,</hi> a most va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant and noble gentleman, and straightway fled into the enemies campe. Some say it was <hi>Bondot,</hi> one of the archers of the Kings guard. When the womans confessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was brought to the King, he immediatly called <hi>Monsieur de Nance,</hi> captaine of his guard, and commanded him to apprehend <hi>Challey</hi> and bring him to him. <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> assoone as hee heard the stroke of the peece, fled into the Kings castle called the Louure, &amp; hid him in the Duke of Guises chamber, from whence he conveyed himself away assoone as he had heard of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:36221:30"/>the Kings commandement. When <hi>de Nance</hi> was informed of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, he answered that <hi>Challey</hi> was a gentleman of good worship, and there was no doubt but if neede were he would appeare before the King and the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates.</p>
            <p>While these things were doing,
<note place="margin">The Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of his life, sends for the King.</note> and the Admirals wound in dres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, <hi>Theligny</hi> went by his coman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement to the King, and most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly besought him in the name of his father in law, that his Majestie would vouchsafe to come unto him for that his life seemed to be in pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill, and that he had certaine things to say, greatly importing to the Kings safety, which he well knew that none in his Realme durst de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to his Majestie. The King cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teously answered that he would willingly go to him, and within a little while after he set forward. The Queen mother went with him and the Duke of Anjow, the Duke of Mondensier, a most affectionate
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:36221:30"/>subject to the Church of Rome,
<note place="margin">The King goes to the Admirall with the Queene mother &amp; others.</note> the County <hi>de Rhetz,</hi> the Queen mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers great familiar, <hi>Chavigny</hi> and <hi>Entragny,</hi> which afterward were chiefe ringleaders in the butchery of Paris.</p>
            <p>When the King had lovingly sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted the Admirall as he was wont to do,
<note place="margin">The Kings loving sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutation of the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</note> and had gently asked him some questions concerning his hurt and the estate of his health, and the Admirall had answered with such a milde and quiet countenance, that all they that were present wondered at his temperance and patience, the King being much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved (as it seem'd) said, The hurt,
<note place="margin">The Kings deepe oath severely to revenge the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals hurt.</note> my Admirall, is done to thee, but the dishonour to me: but (swearing a great oath) saith he, I sweare I will so severely revenge both the hurt and the dishonour, that it shall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be forgotten. He asked him also how he liked of the Judges that he had chosen, to whom he had given commission for examining the matter. The Admirall answered
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:36221:31"/>that he could not but very well like of those that his Majestie had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed of, yet he besought him if he thought it good, that <hi>Cavagnes</hi> might be called to counsell with them, albeit that it was no hard matter to find out, for it was no doubt (said he) that this good turne was done him by the Duke of <hi>Guise,</hi> the revenge whereof he referred to God.
<note place="margin">The Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treats the King to enquire straitly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fact. And the Kings kind Answer.</note> This only he most heartily and humbly besought of his royall Majestie, that the fact might be dulie enquired into. The King an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered that he would take ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest care of it, and revenge that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurie with no lesse severity than if it had been done to himselfe. Then the Kings brethren and their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther withdrawing themselves a while,
<note place="margin">The Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall faithfully advises the King to beware of treasons against himselfe.</note> the Admirall as it was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward knowne by his owne report, began to advise the King to have in memorie those things that he had oft told him of the dangerous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions of certaine persons and he told him, that though he himselfe
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:36221:31"/>had received a great wound, yet there was no lesse hanging over the Kings head: and that long ago there was treason in practizing against his life, which if he would do wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he should avoyd betimes. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he said, that though so soone as God should take him to himselfe out of this life, he doubted not but that his fame should be brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to sundry slanders by envious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, and such as ought him e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill will by reason of the late wars, neverthelesse he had oftentimes disclosed unto the King the authors of the dissentions, and opened the causes thereof, and that God was his witnesse of his most faithfull heart to the King and the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale, and that he had never hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den any thing dearer then his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey and the publique safetie.</p>
            <p>The King after such answer made hereunto as hee thought best, spake aloud, and heartily entreated the Admirall to suffer himselfe to be removed into his castell of the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:36221:32"/>Louure,
<note place="margin">The King under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of sedition feared, desires the Admirall to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle of Louure.</note> for that he thought some perill, lest there should arise some sedition among the commons al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready in disorder, or any stirre in that madde and troublesome Citie. Wherto this speech of the King tended could not then be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood. For though the commonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Paris hath ever been accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the most foolish and madde of al other, yet is it ever most easily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peased, not onely with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and presence of the King, but also with the very sound of his name. The Admiral most humbly and largely thanked the King, and made his excuse upon the counsell of the Phisicians,
<note place="margin">The Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall, by the advise of the Physiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire not to remove.</note> which feared that shak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing would encrease his paine, and therefore had taken order that he should not be stir'd out of his place. Then the Count <hi>de Rhetz</hi> turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to certaine Gentle-men of the Admirals friends, said, I would the Admirall would follow the Kings counsell, for it is to be feared that some such stir may arise in the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:36221:32"/>Towne, as the King shall not easily be able to appease. Which speech being vnttered, although no man did yet suspect whereto that advise tended,
<note place="margin">The Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests a Guard for his safety, to which the King willingly yeelds.</note> yet the Admirall and his friends thought it good to request of the King to assigne unto him cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the souldiers of the Guard for his safetie. The King answered that he very well liked of that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vise, &amp;p that he was fully determin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to provide as wel for the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals safetie as for his owne,
<note place="margin">The Kings high ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions of love and praise to the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall.</note> and that he would preserve the Admirall as the ball of his eye, and that he had in admiration the constancie and fortitude of the man, and that he never before that time beleeved that there could be so great valiant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of courage in any mortall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son.</p>
            <p>Therewith the Duke of Anjow the kings brother cōmanded <hi>Cossin</hi> Captaine of the Kings Guard,
<note place="margin">The Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirals Guard placed.</note> to place a certaine band of Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to ward before the Admirals gate. There could hardly a man
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:36221:33"/>be found more hatefull against the Admirals part, nor more affected to the Guisians then this <hi>Cossin,</hi> which the successe plainly proved, as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after shall apeare.
<note place="margin">The Duke of Anjow causes the Admirals friends to be placed in those lodgings neer about him, under pretence of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirals safeguard, and others to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooved from their lodgings, which was a most de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villish plot to bring in the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants out of the suburbs, from whence they might perhaps have escaped into one narrow street within the wals, that they could not possible avoyd their plotted destruction.</note> The Duke of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jow further added, that he thought it should be good for the Admirall, if moe of his friends and familiars that lodged in the fauxburges did drawe nearer about him: and forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he commanded the Kings harbingers to warn those to whom they had before assigned lodgings in that street, to remove from thence, and to place the Admirals friends in their roomes. Which counsell was such, as none could possibly be devised more fit for those things that followed. For those which might have by flight escaped out of the suburbs were now holden fast enough, being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>closed not only within the wals of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:36221:33"/>the Towne, but also within the compasse of one narrow street. The next day after,
<note place="margin">The names of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants strictly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, with the place of every of their lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings.</note> the Under-masters of the streets, commonly called Quarter-men, surveyed all the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctualling houses and Innes, from house to house, and all the names of those of the <hi>Religion,</hi> together with the place of every of their lodgings they put in bookes, and with speed delivered over the same bookes to those of whom they had received that command.</p>
            <p>In the afternoon, the Queen mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lead out the King, the Duke of Anjow, <hi>Gonzague, Tavaignes,</hi> the County <hi>de Rhetz,</hi> called <hi>Gondin,</hi> into her Gardens called <hi>Tegliers.</hi> This place, because it was somwhat farre from resort, she thought most fit for this their last consultation. There she shewed them, how those whom they had long been in wait for, were now sure in hold, and the Admirall lay in his bed mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of both his armes and could not stirre, the King of Navarre
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:36221:34"/>and the Prince of Conde were fast lodged in the Castle,
<note place="margin">The King and the Queene consults a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their last most bloudy and devil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figne.</note> the gates were kept shut all night, and watches placed, so as they were so snared that they could no way escape, and the Captains thus taken, it was not to be feared that any of the <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> would from thenceforth stir any more. Now was a notable oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity (said she) offered to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch the matter. For all the chiefe Captaines were fast closed up in Paris, and the rest in other Towns were all unarmed and unprepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and that there were scarcely to be found ten enemies to a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Catholikes: that the Parisians were in armour and were able to make threescore thousand chosen fighting men, and that within the space of one houre all the enimies may be slayne, and the whole name and race of those wicked men be vtterly rooted out. On the other side (saith she) if the King do not take the advantage of the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of this time, it is no doubt but
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:36221:34"/>that if the Admirall recover his health, all France wil shortly be on fire with the fourth civill war.</p>
            <p>The Queenes opinion was allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Howbeit it was thought best, partly for his age, and partly for the affinities sake, that the King of Navarres life should be saved. As for the Prince of Conde, it was doubted whether it were best to spare him for his age, or to put him to death for hatred of his fathers name.
<note place="margin">The King and the Queene consults to put this designe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and committed the doing of it to the Duke of Guise.</note> But herein the opinion of <hi>Gonzague</hi> took place, that he should with feare of death and torment, be drawne from the <hi>Religion.</hi> So that counsell brake up, with appoynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that the matter should be put in execution the next night early afore day, and that the ordering and doing of all should be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Duke of Guise.</p>
            <p>The Admirall being enformed of stirre and noyse of armour, and threatnings heard every where throughout the towne, and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of many things pertaining to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:36221:35"/>tumult,
<note place="margin">The King sends to the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, to take away all suspition of feare.</note> sent word thereof to the King: who answered, that there was no cause for the Admirall to feare, for all was done by his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and not every where, but in certaine places, &amp; that there were certaine appointed by him to be in armor, lest the people should rise and make any stir in the Towne.</p>
            <p>When the Duke of <hi>Guise</hi> thought all things readie enough,
<note place="margin">The Duke of Guise causeth the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers to be assembled to declare the Kings minde, which was to destroy al the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants, which hee now stiles Rebels, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing his former acts of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and Pacifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> he called to him the abovesaid <hi>Marcell,</hi> and charged him that he should a little after midnight assemble together the Masters of the streets whom they call Diziners into the Towne house, for he had certaine strange and speciall matters in charge from the King, which his pleasure was to have declared unto them. They all assembled betimes, <hi>Carron</hi> the new Provost of Merchants, guarded with certaine <hi>Guisians,</hi> and among the rest <hi>Entragne</hi> and <hi>Pnygallart,</hi> made the declaration: He said that the Kings meaning was to destroy all the Rebels which
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:36221:35"/>had in these late yeares borne armes against his Majestie, and to root out the race of those wicked men, it was now very fitly happened that the Chieftaines and ringleaders of them were fast enclosed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the walles of the Towne, as in a prison, and that the same night they should first begin with them, and afterward for the rest as soone as possibly might be, throughout all parts of the Realme the King would take order: and the token to set upon them, should be given, not with a trumpet,
<note place="margin">Tokens to distinguish who was to bee slaine and who not.</note> but with <hi>tock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sein</hi> or ringing of the great bell of the Pallace, which they knew to be accustomed only in great cases: and the mark for them to be known from other, should be a white lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen cloath hanged about their left arme, and a white crosse pinned up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their caps. In the meane time the Duke of <hi>Guise</hi> made privie thereunto the captains of the Kings guard, both <hi>Gascoignes, Frenchmen,</hi> and <hi>Switzers,</hi> &amp; bad them be ready
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:36221:36"/>to go to it with good courage. Short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after, the Duke of Guise and the bastard sonne of king <hi>Henry,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> with a great band of armed men follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, went to the Admirals house, which <hi>Cossin</hi> kept besieged with Harquebuziers, placed in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der on both sides of the street.</p>
            <p>The Admirall advertised of the stirre and the noise of the armour, although hee had scarcely ten per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons in his house able to beare har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and in his chamber only two Surgeons, one Preacher, and one or two servitors, yet could not be made afraid, trusting (as he oft rehearsed) upon the <hi>Kings good will toward him,</hi> approved by so many and so great meanes of assurance, having also confidence that the <hi>Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty of Paris</hi> if they once under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood the king to mislike of their mad fury, how much soever they were in outrage, yet so soon as they saw <hi>Cossin</hi> warding the gate, they would be appeased. He repeated
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:36221:36"/>also the <hi>Oath for keeping of the Peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miralls confidence being hardly brought to feare, notwith standing all these stirs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering. The divers ratifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of peace by the King, his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Oaths so often, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on record, Leagues, Mariages, publique Faith. The sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of the Law of Nations, &amp;c.</note>
               <hi>so oft openly sworne by the King and his brethren, and their Mother, and entred in publique re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, the league lately made with the Queene of England for the same cause, the Articles of treatie co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanted with the Prince of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renge, the Kings faith given to the Princes of Germany, some Townes attempted and some taken in the Low-countrey by the Kings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, the marriage of the Kings Sister solemnized but six dayes before, which it was not like that he would suffer to bee defiled with bloud: finally the judgement of forren nations &amp; of posterity, shame, and the honour and constancie of a Prince, publique Faith, and the sa / cred respect of the law of Nations;</hi> all which it seemed monstrous and incredible that the king could assent to be stained with so outragious a cruell deed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cossin,</hi> when he saw the Noble / men draw neare, knocked at the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:36221:37"/>gate, which as is above-said, he was commanded by the Duke of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jow to keepe. Whereupon many applyed the old proverbe, <hi>A good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly guard to make the Wolfe keeker of the sheepe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cossin,</hi> the Captain of the Guard before the Admirals<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters the gate, slew all within the porch at the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</note> When hee was entred without (in a manner) any difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, he carryed in with him a great company of armed men, and after those followed the great Lords. Such as <hi>Cossin</hi> found at the entry of and within the porch of the house, he slew with a Partisan that he had in his hand. Which when the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall understood, he caused those that were about him to lift him out of his bed, and casting on a night-gowne upon him, he rose up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right on his feet, he bade his friends and servants to flee and make shift for themselves, and to take no more care for him, for he said that he was ready with most willing heart to render into the hands of God, now calling for it againe, the spirit that hee had lent him to use for a time: and said that this vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:36221:37"/>cruelty was prepared not so much for his destruction,
<note place="margin">The Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects now, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares to dye.</note> as for the dishonouring of Christ and the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting of so many Churches, the defence of which Churches he had at the petition of all godly men with his many dangers and cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities sustained.</p>
            <p>In the meane time there came up the staires into the upper part of the house,
<note place="margin">They break into the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</note> one <hi>Benvese</hi> a <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine,</hi> brought up in the house of the Duke of <hi>Guise,</hi> and to whom it is saide, that the Cardinall of <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine</hi> had given one of his bastard daughters in marriage: and with him came <hi>Cossin</hi> the <hi>Gascoin, Attin</hi> a <hi>Picarde</hi> a retainer and familiar of the Duke <hi>d'Aumal,</hi> one that a few yeares before sought to murther <hi>d'Andelot</hi> by treason, and also one <hi>Hamfort</hi> an <hi>Avernois,</hi> all weapon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with swords and targets, and armed with shirts of maile.</p>
            <p>When they were broken into the Admirals chamber, <hi>Benvese</hi> came to him, and bending his drawn
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:36221:38"/>sword upon him, said, Art not thou the Admirall? he with a quiet and constant countenance, (as we have since understood by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves) answered, I am so called. And then seeing the sword drawn upon him, hee said, young man, consider my age and the weak case that I am now in.
<note place="margin">One blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming God, runs his sword into the Admirall, and strikes him. Another shootes him.</note> But the fellow, after blaspheming God, first thrust his sword into the Admirals brest, and then also strucke him upon the head, and <hi>Attin</hi> shot him thorow the brest with a pistol. When the Admiral was with this wound not yet throughly dead, <hi>Benvese</hi> gave him the third wound upon the thigh, and so he fell downe for dead.
<note place="margin">They wound him the third time, so he falls downe dead.</note> When the Duke of Guise, which stayed in the court with the other noble men, heard this, he cried out alowd, hast thou done <hi>Benvese?</hi> he answered, I have done. Then said the Duke of Guise, our <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velier</hi> (meaning King <hi>Henries</hi> ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stard abovesaid) unlesse hee see it with his eyes, will not beleeve it
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:36221:38"/>throw him downe at the window. Then <hi>Benvese</hi> with the help of his fellowes tooke up the Admirals body and threw it downe thorow the window.
<note place="margin">At the Duke of <hi>Guises</hi> command they throw him out at a window.</note> When by reason of the wound in his head, and his face covered with blood they could not well discerne him,
<note place="margin">The Duke of <hi>Guise</hi> gratulates their hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding to go on, crying out This is the Kings command, his will, his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure.</note> the Duke of <hi>Guise</hi> kneeled downe on the ground and wiped him with a nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin and said, now I know him, it is he. And therewithall going out at the gate with the rest of the Lords, he cred out to the multitude armour, saying my companions we have had good lucky beginning: now let us go forward to the rest, for it is the Kings commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: which words hee did oft re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peate alowd, saying, <hi>Thus the King commandeth: This is the Kings will, this is his pleasure.</hi> And then he commanded the token to be given by ringing <hi>tocksein</hi> with the great bell of the pallace, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larme to be raised, and he caused it to be published, that the conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratours
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:36221:39"/>were in armour and about to kill the King. Then a certain <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> of <hi>Gonzagues</hi> band,
<note place="margin">One cuts off his head, other his hands, other his secret parts, they drag him thorow the streets, hangs him by the feet.</note> cut off the Admirals head, and sent it preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with spices to Rome to the Pope and the Cardinall of <hi>Loraine.</hi> Other cut off his hands, and other his secret parts. Then the common labourers and rascals three daies to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether dragged the dead body thus mangled and berayed with blood and filth, thorow the streets, and afterward drew it out of the towne to the common gallowes, and hanged it up with a rope by the feet.
<note place="margin">The Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirals most cruel and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous death, with all about him, the end and issue of all the Kings grace and favour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In the meane time, those of the noble mens bands brake into all the chambers of the Admirals house, and such as they found either in their beds, or hidden, they mang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them with many wounds, and so slaughtered them. Of that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber were two young children, pages, of honourable birth. There was also the Counte <hi>Rochfoucault,</hi> which for the excellent pleasent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:36221:39"/>of his wit, and for his va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liantnesse was highly beloved of King <hi>Henry,</hi> and so seemed for the same cause also to be beloved of the King. Him was <hi>de Nance</hi> above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said commanded to kill, but he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusing it for their old accquaintance and familiarity: one <hi>Laberge</hi> an <hi>Avernois</hi> offered himselfe to the King to do it, but with this condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the King should give him the captaineship of horse-men which Count <hi>Rochfoucault</hi> had.
<note place="margin">Counte <hi>Rochfou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cault</hi> slain. <hi>Theligny</hi> the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals son in law slaine.</note> There was also slayne <hi>Theligny</hi> the Admirals son in law, a young man of singular towardnesse both of wit and courage, to whom the King these many yeares had both in words and countenance made shew of so great good will, as that no man was thought to be more highly in his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor. He crying out, that it was now grievious to him to live, for that he had ever commended to his father in law the faithfulnesse of the King, refused not the death offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him. And many other most
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:36221:40"/>flourishing young noble men and gentlemen were every where but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherly murthered in that street.
<note place="margin">Many gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered in the streets.</note> Then the noble mens bands, and <hi>Cossins</hi> souldiers went ransacking from house to house: and the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirals house and al the other houses were all sacked and spoyled,
<note place="margin">The sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and spoilings by the souldiers.</note> even in like manner as is used to be done by souldiers greedy of prey in a Towne taken by assault: and many by this robbery, were of beggers suddenly become rich men. For the Duke of <hi>Guise,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Monpensier,</hi> the <hi>Chevalier</hi> King <hi>Henries</hi> bastard, <hi>Gonzague, Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaignes,</hi> and the other great Lords, did with reward of the spoyle and bootie encourage the multitude to the slaughter, and cried out aloud that this was the Kings will.
<note place="margin">They cry out still This is the Kings wil.</note> So all the rest of the day from morning to evening, the rascall multitude, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by spoyle and robberie, ran with their bloudy swords rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thorowout al the Towne: they spared not the aged, nor women,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:36221:40"/>nor the very babes:
<note place="margin">The streets strewed with mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies.</note> In joy and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph they threw the slayne bodies out at the windowes, so as there was not in manner any one street or lane, that seemed not strewed with murthered car cases.</p>
            <p>While these things were thus a doing in the Towne, the King of <hi>Navarre</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> whom the King had lodged in his owne castle of the <hi>Louure,</hi> were by the Kings commandement sent for and conveyed unto him.
<note place="margin">The King of <hi>Navar,</hi> and Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitours, friends, hewed in pieces and slaine, themselves sent for to the King.</note> But their company, their servitours of their chamber, their friends retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them, their schole-masters, and those that had the bringing up of them, crying out alowd to the Kings fidelity for succour, were thrust out of the chambers, and by the Kings guard of <hi>Switzers</hi> hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in pieces and slaughtered in the Kings owne sight. But of that number of persons slayne, no mans case was so much lamented of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, as <hi>Monsieur de Pilles,</hi> in whom it is hard to expresse whether there
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:36221:41"/>were more godly zeale in <hi>Religion,</hi> or prowesse in warre. Whereby having in the late yeares, specially by the defence of the Towne of Saint <hi>Iohn d' Angeli,</hi> which the King then besieged, gotten great honour of <hi>Chevalry,</hi> he was thought very well beloved and highly esteemed of the King. Him and <hi>Leranne</hi> the son of <hi>Odou,</hi> by the <hi>French</hi> Kings commandement (which was not then understood whereto ittended) the King of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>var</hi> had staied in a wardrob adjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to his own chamber, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed them to lodge there all night. A little afore day, hearing of the running of men, and noise of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and cryes and killings, they rose in hast, &amp; immediatly <hi>de Nance</hi> whom we have before spoken of, came to them, and cōmanded them in the Kings name to come downe into the Court, and to leave their weapons behind them, and lastly to depart out of the castle. When <hi>de Pilles</hi> saw himselfe thrust out
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:36221:41"/>among the multitude of the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering souldiers,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Monsieur de Pilles</hi> seemingly much e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steemed of the King, treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously slaine. He detests the Kings traytero is infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the Kings hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</note> and beheld the bodies of them that were slaine; he cryed out with a very lowd voyce, that the King might well heare him, protesting upon the Kings fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity, and detesting his trayterous infidelity, and therwith he took off a rich cloak which he wore, and gave it to one of his acquaintance, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, take here this token of <hi>Pilles,</hi> and hereafter remember <hi>Pilles</hi> most unworthily and shamefuly slaine. Oh my good <hi>Monsieur de Pilles,</hi> said the other, I am none of them: I thanke you for your cloake, but I will not receive it with that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and so refused to take the cloake: and immediately <hi>de Pilles</hi> was thrust thorow by one of the Guard with a Partisan, and died. And this end had this most valiant and Noble Gentleman. And then his body was throwne into the quarrey with the rest; which when they that passed by did behold, the souldiers cryed out, there they
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:36221:42"/>be that made assault upon us, and would have killed the King. <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranne</hi> being thrust thorow with a sword, escaped and ran into the Queen of <hi>Navarres</hi> chamber, and was by her kept and preserved from the violence of those that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sued him. Shortly after, she obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his pardon of her brother, and committing him to her owne Physitians, restored him both to life and health.</p>
            <p>While things were in doing at <hi>Paris, Strozzi,</hi> which (as we have aforesaid) was come with all his power to <hi>Rochel,</hi> sent a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of his souldiers into the Town, under colour of a banket to be made to his friends in the castell called <hi>la Chein,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Civell treason under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of a banquet.</note> but by reason of the jealousie and watches of the townes men, by whom hee saw his treason was espied, he went away without his purpose. But they of <hi>la Charity,</hi> which as we have before shewed, were trapped by the <hi>Italian</hi> horse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, taking lesse heed to the safe
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:36221:42"/>keeping of their Towne, were a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before night surprized, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in few daies after put to the sword.</p>
            <p>The next day following, where a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that had hidden themselves in corners at <hi>Paris</hi> could be found out the slaughter was renewed:
<note place="margin">The slaughter renewed the next day.</note> also common labourers and porters, and other of the most rascals of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and desperate villaines,
<note place="margin">They strip the dead bodies and threw them into the river <hi>Seane.</hi>
               </note> to have the spoyle of their clothes, stripped the dead bodies stark naked and threw them into the river of <hi>Seane.</hi> The profit of all the robberies and spoyles came all for the most part to the hands of these laborers and the souldiers, and to the Kings trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure came very little or nothing. The only gaine that came to him, was that which might be made of the vacations (as they terme them) of offices and of places of Magistrates, Captaines and other rooms of charge, wherof yet he gave a great part freely away to divers of the Court. For the Admirals of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice he gave to Marques <hi>d'Villars,</hi>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:36221:43"/>the Chancellorship of <hi>Navarre,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirals Office, &amp; other Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed of.</note> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the murther of <hi>Francourt,</hi> he by and by gave to <hi>Henry Memne de Malassise,</hi> which had been the truceman and messenger in the Treaty of the last peace: the Office of the Master of the Finances after the slaughter of <hi>Prunes</hi> he gave to <hi>Villequier,</hi> the Office of President <hi>des aides,</hi> when <hi>Plateau</hi> was slaine he gave to <hi>de Nully:</hi> the other Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices hee sold, as his manner is, to such as gave ready mony for them. For it hath been the custome now lately of certaine Kings of <hi>France</hi> (such as among forren Nations hath not been heard of) to put to sale all the profits, rights, and benefits of of the Crown,
<note place="margin">Offices sold for ready mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</note> and to keep an open market for money, of all judiciall Offices, and of the Roomes belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Treasure and Fiances, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to a rate of price set upon every one of them:
<note place="margin">Vendere jure potest, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anerat ille prius.</note> and there is not in manner one in all <hi>France,</hi> that doth not openly justifie that hee bought his Office for ready money,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:36221:43"/>and that no man ought to marvell if he desire to fill up the empty hole of his stock againe. And therefore Justice is thorow all <hi>France</hi> usual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bought for money, and though there be never so many murthers committed, yet is there no Processe awarded to enquire thereof, till pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent coyne be payd to the rake-hels and scribes.</p>
            <p>This butcherly slaughter of <hi>Paris</hi> thus performed, and foure hundred houses (as is above-said) sacked, immediately messengers were sent in post into all parts of the Realme,
<note place="margin">Letters in the Kings name to all other Cities, to follow the example of <hi>Paris</hi> in this blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sacre.</note> with oft shifting their horses for haste, to command all other Cities in the Kings name to follow the example of <hi>Paris,</hi> and to cause to be killed as many as they had among them of the reformed <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These commandements it is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful to tel how readily and cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully the greatest part of the Cities of <hi>France</hi> did obey and execute. But the King, fearing (as it was likely) the dishonour of false trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:36221:44"/>and perjury,
<note place="margin">The King fearing the dishonour of treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, sends Letters to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to <hi>England, Germany, Switzer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare in his name the great commoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which was hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, and his owne sorrow for them.</note> sent letters to the Governours of his Provinces, and also speedy Messengers into <hi>England, Germany</hi> and <hi>Zwitzer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to declare in his name, that there was a great commotion and seditious stir happened at <hi>Paris,</hi> which he was very sory for: that the Duke of <hi>Guise</hi> had raised the people, and with armed men made assault upon the band that was as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed to the Admiral for his guard, and had broken into the house and slaine the Admiral and all his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany and houshold servants, and that the King had hardly kept safe from those dangers his own Castell of the <hi>Louure,</hi> where he kept him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe close with his mother and his brethren: the true copy of which letters is hereafter inserted. But the same most mighty, and by the consent of all Nations commonly called the most Christian King, within two dayes after came into the Parliament, accompanied with a great traine of his brethren and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:36221:44"/>other Princes. The Councell being assembled, he fitting in his throne,
<note place="margin">The King after these Letters sent, comes to his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, declares hee was certified of the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and therefore comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him to be slain.</note> began to speak unto them, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared that he was certified, that the Admirall with certain of his complices had conspired his death, and had intended the like purpose against his brethren, the Queen his mother, and the King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> and that for this cause he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his friends to slay the said Admirall and all his confederates, and so to prevent the treason of his enemies.</p>
            <p>This his testification and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
<note place="margin">This testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be written, recorded, published.</note> the King commanded to be written and entered in the records of Parliament, and that it should be proclaimed by the Harolds, and published by Printers. And he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a booke to be set forth to this effect, that the slaughter of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral and his adherentes was done by the Kings commandement, for so was his Majesty expresse pleasure, because they had conspired to kill him &amp; his brethren, and the Queen
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:36221:45"/>his mother, and the king of <hi>Navar.</hi> And further,
<note place="margin">The King forbids all assemblies and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching used of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing it was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the first article granted in the Acts of Pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, that they should have their liberty. The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sident of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament gratulates the Kings guile and subtilty in conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his enemies.</note> that the King did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid that from thence-forth there should be no more assemblies hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, nor preachings used of the <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the Kings Oration ended, <hi>Christopher Thuane</hi> President of that Parliament, a man very notable for his light brain &amp; his cruel heart, did with very large words congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulate unto the King, that he had now with guile and subtilty over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come these his enemies, whom he could never vanquish by armes and battell, saying that therein the King had most fully verified the old say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Lews</hi> 11. his progenitor, King of <hi>France,</hi> which was wont to say that he knew never a Latin sentence but this one, <hi>Qui nescit dissimulare nescit regnare,</hi> He that cannot skill to dissemble, cannot skill to be a King, But <hi>Pibrace,</hi> the advocate of the Finances, made a short oration, the summe whereof was to this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, that although the king had just
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:36221:45"/>and great cause to be displeased, yet he thought it more agreeable with his Majesties clemency &amp; goodnes, to make an end of the slaughters &amp; common spoile, &amp; not to suffer such outrages to be any longer commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted without judiciall proceeding in the cause:
<note place="margin">The King is at last desired to proceed in a judiciall way. Whereto the King assents, and the murthers cease.</note> and besought his Majesty that from thence-forth it would please him to use the law, which is well known to be the only stablish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Kingdomes and Empires: and that there had been already gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the commonalty too peril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous an example to follow. An ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest of Parliament with the Kings royall assent being made to that ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, there were immediately Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolds and trumpeters sent round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout all the town, and an Edict pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed in the Kings name, that from thence-forth the slaughters and common butcherly murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings should cease, and that all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons should abstaine from pillage and robbery.</p>
            <p>This being known, there were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:36221:46"/>speeces used of this matter thorowout the Towne, and speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of learned men. The most part said, that they had read many Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stories, but in all memory of all ages they never heard of any such thing as this.
<note place="margin">The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parison of this slaughter with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but this excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all.</note> They compared this case with the horrible doings of King <hi>Mithridates,</hi> which with one Messenger and with the advertise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of one letter, caused a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth and fifty thousand <hi>Romaines</hi> to be slaine. Some compared it with the doing of <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Arra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon,</hi> which slew eight thousand <hi>Frenchmen</hi> in <hi>Sicile,</hi> w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> Isle they had surprised in his absence. But yet this difference appeared between those cases and this: that those Kings had exercised their cruelty upon forreners &amp; strangers: but this King had done his outrage upon his own subjects, being yeelded not so much to his power, as to his faith &amp; credit. Those Kings were bound by no promise but such as was given to the strangers themselves:
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:36221:46"/>this King was with new made league bound to the Kings &amp; Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces his neighbours to keep the peace that he had sworne.
<note place="margin">This hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid fact aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> Those Kings used no guilefull meanes unworthy for the Majesty of a King, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive: this King for a bait and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurement abused the marriage of his owne sister, and in a manner be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sprinkled her wedding robe with blood. Which dishonour and indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity no posterity of al ages can for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get. Some againe discoursed, that though this cruell advise seemed to many Courtiers to have been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, yet not onely the honour of a King, but also the estimation and good fame of the whole nation was against that shew of profit, They al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged how <hi>Aristides</hi> did openly in the audience of al the people, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the counsell of <hi>Themistocles</hi> concerning the burning of the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedemonians</hi> navy, although it must needs have followed, that the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies should therby have bin utterly weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:36221:47"/>
               <hi>Furius Camillus</hi> received not the children of the chiefe Lords of the <hi>Phalisce,</hi> betrayed to him by their Schoole-master, but stripped him naked and delivered him to be whipped home with rods by the fame children.
<note place="margin">The cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon,</hi> for the light e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steeme of his oath.</note>
               <hi>Pausanias</hi> hath left it reported that the posterity of <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi> fell into most great calamities, for this cause, that he was wont to set light by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend conscience of an oath and his faith given in leagues. Some cited the law of the twelve tables: <hi>Si patronus clienti fraudem facit, sacer esto.</hi> If the patrone or sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne defraud his client or vassal, be he out of protection. They dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted also, that like faith as the vas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal oweth to his Lord, the Lord ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth also to his vassal: and for what causes and for what fellonies the vassall loseth his tenancy, for the same causes and fellonies the Lord loseth his segniory. Some said that the right hand in ancient time was called the pledge of the faith of a
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:36221:47"/>King, and that this if a King shall despise, there is no communion of right with him, and he is no more to be accounted a King, neither of his owne subjects nor of strangers.
<note place="margin">Kingly vertues.</note> Kingly vertues in times past have been reported to be these, justice, gentlenesse and clemency: but cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty and outrage have ever been dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praised both in all persons and specially in Princes.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Scipia's</hi> praise.</note>
               <hi>Scipio</hi> hath in all ages been praysed, who was wont to say, that he had rather save one Citizen than kill a thousand enemies: which sentence <hi>Antoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> the Emperour, surnamed <hi>Pius</hi> the kind or vertuous, did oft repeat. It was a most shamefull by word of young <hi>Tiberius</hi> to be called <hi>Clay</hi> tempered with blood.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tiberius</hi> call'd <hi>Clay</hi> temper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with bloud.</note> They said also, that Kings have power of life and death over their subjects, but not without hearing the cause, and judiciall proceeding:
<note place="margin">The Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators power at <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </note> that there cannot be alleaged a greater autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, than the dictators had at <hi>Rome,</hi> in whom was the soveraign power
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:36221:48"/>of peace and war, of life and death, and without appeale, yet was it not lawfull for them to execute a Citizen his cause unheard. Only theeves and murderers take away mens lives without order of law and hearing their cause. Who can doubt (said they) but that this so great outrage, so great shedding of Christian blood is the fruit of the cursed life of the Courtiers? For (said they) now thorow-out all <hi>France</hi> whoredome and loose lewdnesse of life are so free &amp; usu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,
<note place="margin">The wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ednesse and licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiousnesse thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>France</hi> after this.</note> that now the most part of the women of <hi>France</hi> seeme to be in manner common: and the wicked blasphemies and continuall execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and dishonourings of Gods most holy name and Majesty, are such as God cannot longer beare: and true it is, though incredible among forren Nations, that the Catholikes of <hi>France</hi> have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed themselves this for a special marke to bee knowne from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men, that at every third
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:36221:48"/>word they blasphemously swear by the head, death, bloud,
<note place="margin">The Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. The King himselfe delights in it.</note> and belly of God: and wonderfull it is, that the King himselfe is so much delighted in this custome of swearing and blaspheming: and this as it were a pestilent infection is spred abroad and common among the very plowmen and paysants, so as none among them now speaketh three words without most filthy blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming and horrible execration of God. Who can longer beare the vile vnchastities, the bawds and ruffians of the Court? Finally, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry nature it self doth now as it were expostulate with God for his so long sufferance and forbearing, and the earth can no longer beare these monsters.</p>
            <p>Now as touching the Admirals supposed conspiracy, who can thinke it likely that hee should en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprise any such thing within the walles of <hi>Paris?</hi> For in the Court there is continuall watching and warding a garrison of the Kings:
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:36221:49"/>and at the entry of his Castle the guardes of <hi>Gascoines, Scots</hi> and <hi>Switzers,</hi> are continually attending and the King himself both alwayes before, and specially at that time, by reason of his sisters mariage, had a great trayne of Princes, great Lords, noblemen and gentlemen about him. Moreover it was well knowne,
<note place="margin">The great improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of any trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son which was sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed on the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals part.</note> that in <hi>Paris</hi> within three houres space might be assembled &amp; put in armour threescore thousand chosen armed men, specially against the Admirall, whom no man is ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant that <hi>Parisians</hi> most deadly hated: beside that, the noble young men that came thither with the King of <hi>Navarre</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> by reason of the mariage, and brought with them their wives, their sisters and their kins<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women, thought at that time upon nothing but upon triumph &amp; exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cises of pastime, and gay furniture of apparell and ornaments. Finally, at whether of these two times can it be likely that the Admirall
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:36221:49"/>attempted this conspiracy? Was it before he was hurt? why? at that time hee found the King his most loving, or at least his most liberall and bountifull good Lord: neither could hee hope ever to have a more favourable Soveraigne in <hi>France.</hi> Was it then after he was hurt? as though, forsooth, he lying sore of two so great wounds, aged, mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of both his armes, the one whereof the Physitians consulted whether it were to be cut off, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with three hundreth young men, would set upon three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>score thousand armed men, or in so small a time could lay the plot for so great, and so long, and so hainous a fact: for he lived scarce 40. houres after his hurt, in which time he was enjoyned by the Physitians to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare talk. Again, if he had been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected of any such crime, was hee not committed to <hi>Cossin,</hi> and to his keeping, and so environed, all the wayes beset about him; and so in the Kings power, that if it had plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:36221:50"/>the King he might at all times in a moment be carried to prison? Why was not orderly enquiry and judicial proceeding used according to the custome and lawes, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall right of Nations, and witnesses produced according to the forme of law? But be it that the Admirall and a few other of his confederates and followers had conspired, why yet proceeded the outragious cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty upon the rest that were innocent, why upon ancient matrons, why upon noble Ladies, and young Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen and Virgins that came thither for the honour of the wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding?
<note place="margin">Ladies, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women, Virgins, Counsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitians, learned Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants, and among the rest <hi>Petrus Ramus</hi> slaine.</note> Why were so many women great with child, against the Lawes of all Nations and of nature, before their delivery throwne into the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver? Why were so many aged per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, many that lay sick in their beds, many gowne-men, many Counsellers, Advocates, Proctors, Physitians, many singularly learned professours and teachers of good Artes, and among the rest <hi>Petrus
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:36221:50"/>Ramus</hi> that renowmed man tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row-out the world, many young Students executed without hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, without pleading their cause, without sentence of condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Moreover, if the Admirall had slain the three brethren, who doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth but that all Countries, all Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, all Parliaments; finally, all sorts and degrees of men would have speedily taken armour, and easily have destroyed all of the <hi>Religion,</hi> having them enclosed within their Townes, and having just cause to render to all forren nations for their common slaughters and killing of them?
<note place="margin">The ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surdity of the suspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Admirals treason a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the King of <hi>Navarre.</hi>
               </note> As to that which toucheth the King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> what can be imagined more absurd &amp; unlikely? Had not the Admirall him foure yeares in his power? Did not hee professe the same <hi>Religion</hi> that the Admirall did? Which of those of the <hi>Religion,</hi> which of them I say (as <hi>Cassius</hi> was wont to reason) should have gained or received pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by the killing of the King of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varre?</hi>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:36221:51"/>did not the Catholikes hate him? and the Admirall could not hope to have any man more friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to him, nor by any other mans meanes to have revenge of his injury. Lastly, in their houses that were slaine, what armour, what weapons were found, by which conjectures Judges use to be led to trace out a fact? These matters wise men throughout the Towne of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> commonly muttered.</p>
            <p>But now to returne to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose. At such time as the Kings pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition abovesaid was preclaimed at <hi>Paris,</hi> not only in other Towns, as at <hi>Orleaunce,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thertowns.</note>
               <hi>Angiers, Viaron Troyes,</hi> and <hi>Auxerre,</hi> the like but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries and slaughters were used, but also in the Towne of <hi>Paris</hi> it selfe, in the very gaoles that are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for the keeping of prisoners, if any had escaped the cruelty of the day before, they were now tumultuously slayne by the raging and outraging multitude, in which number were three Gentlemen
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:36221:51"/>of great reputation,
<note place="margin">The priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered in gaoles, whereof three gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen was slaine among the rest, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, Lomen</hi> the Kings Secretary, <hi>Chappes</hi> a Lawyer. <hi>Masson de Rivers</hi> a Pastor of the Church, the first that laid the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Church of <hi>Paris,</hi> slaine.</note> Captaine <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nins</hi> a man very famous in Marciall Prowesse, <hi>Lomen</hi> the Kings secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, a man of great estimation for his long service in the Court, and <hi>Chappes</hi> a Lawyer neere four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>score yeare old, a man of great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne in the Court of <hi>Paris.</hi> And because we have made mention of <hi>Angiers,</hi> we think it good not to omit the case of <hi>Masson de Rivers.</hi> This man was a Pastor of the Church, and esteemed a singular man both in vertuousnesse of life, &amp; in excellence of wit and learning, and was the first that had layd the foundation of the Church at <hi>Paris.</hi> As soone as the slaughter was begun at <hi>Paris, Monsorel</hi> a most cruel ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of the <hi>Religion,</hi> was sent to <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giers</hi> in post to prevent al other that might carry tidings of the <hi>Massa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre.</hi> As soone as he came into the Towne, he caused himselfe to be brought to <hi>Massons</hi> house: There he met <hi>Massons</hi> wife in the entry, and gētly saluted her, &amp; after the maner
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:36221:52"/>of <hi>France,</hi> specially of the Court, he kissed her, and asked her where her husband was, she answered, that he was walking in the garden, and by and by shee brought <hi>Monsorel</hi> to her husband, who gently embraced <hi>Masson,</hi> and said unto him: Canst thou tell why I am come hither? It is to kill thee by the Kings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement at this very instant time, for so hath the King com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, as thou mayst perceive by these letters, and therwith he shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him his dag ready charged. <hi>Mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> answered that he was not guilty of any crime, howbeit this one thing only he besought him, to give him space to call to the mercy of God, and to cōmend his spirit into Gods hand. Which prayer as soone as he had ended in few words, he meekly received the death offered by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and was shot thorow with a pellet and dyed.</p>
            <p>Now to returne to <hi>Paris,</hi> the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirals body being hanged up by the heeles upon the common gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:36221:52"/>of <hi>Paris,</hi> as is aforesaid, the <hi>Parisians</hi> went thither by heapes to see it.
<note place="margin">The Qu. goes to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Admirall hanged by the heeles. His body conveyed away se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly, and buried.</note> And the Queen mother to feed her eyes with that spectacle, had a mind also to go thither, and shee carried with her the King and both her other sonnes. But the next night following, the body was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighed away, and (as it is thought) buried. About that time, where as many of the Court secretly mutter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the King should by this fact incurre dishonour, not only among forren Nations, but also with all posterity in time to come for ever, <hi>Morvillier,</hi> of whom we have made mention before, one that was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted the principal lewed practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser and wicked sycophant of all <hi>France,</hi> and the first authour and chiefe mean of bringing the Jesuits into <hi>France,</hi> came to the Queene mother, and told her that it was best that some of those that were lately taken flying &amp; hiding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, should for custome sake be brought to open judgement, and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:36221:53"/>after the accustomed maner should be enquired upon,
<note place="margin">Some brought to open judgment, to wipe off the blot of dishonour from the King.</note> that they might be condemned by the Sentence of certaine Judges pickt out for that purpose, and so openly executed in sight of the people. There were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to counsell hereupon <hi>Birage, Limege, Thuan</hi> and <hi>Belleure.</hi> They not only allowed <hi>Morvilliers</hi> opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
<note place="margin">A man of hay, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals body, drag'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the streets, his Armes and Ensignes broken, his children pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and unable, &amp;c.</note> but also gave advise, that a man of hey made in figure for the Admirall (for his body, as wee have said, could not bee found) should be dragged by the <hi>Boureau</hi> thorow the streets, his armes and ensignes of honour broken, his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory condemned, his Castels and fermes razed, his children pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced infamous, unnoble, and intesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and all the trees in his woods to be hewen down to the height of six foot. There was among those that were apprehended, one <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaignes,</hi> Master of Requests to the King, and <hi>Briquemault,</hi> of whom we have before spoken. This <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quemault</hi> had spent his time in
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:36221:53"/>service in the old warres in the time of King <hi>Francis</hi> and king <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and was for the war accompted a man of great experience among the best now living, and was neare about threescore and ten years old.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cavaignes</hi> and <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quemault</hi> terrified by most cruell tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to make them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse the Admirall and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves traytors.</note> As soone as they were carryed into prison, there were presented unto them all, the tormenter &amp; the hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and they were threatned with torture and tearing their bodies in peeces, unlesse they would present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly subscribe with their owne hand, that they were of counsell with the Admirall to kill the King and his brethren, and the Queen mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the King of <hi>Navarre.</hi> They all cryed out that they were ready to suffer death most wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly forasmuch as the Kings plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure was it should be so: but so great torture they could not beare, and therefore humbly besought his roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all goodnesse and clemency to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don them that torment, and yet trusting upon the mercy of God, they hoped that they should suffer
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:36221:54"/>exceeding great paines, rather than staine themselves with so great shame, or confesse an untrue crime against themselves. They that were first assigned their judges,
<note place="margin">The Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges refuse to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne them.</note> hearing their cries and defences, and fearing the judgement of the world, said plainly that they would not draw upon themselves most assured in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famie for condemning them. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there were new Judges ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in their places:
<note place="margin">New Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed.</note> to them was adjoyned such a tormenter and notary, as were thought fittest for the purpose.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cavaignes</hi> and <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quemault</hi> condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note> And so <hi>Briquemault</hi> and <hi>Cavaignes</hi> were quickly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by a shadowed forme of law, and led to the gibbet stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the principall street of the Towne, and in sight of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands of men gazing at them. To this spectacle the Queene mother led the King and her other sonnes, and her sonne in law, the King of <hi>Navarre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was thought commodious for playing of this last act, that <hi>Brique<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mault</hi>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:36221:54"/>should in hearing of all the people aske pardon of the King, and for that purpose there were some suborned to put him in mind, that if hee would hee might easily purchase his life,
<note place="margin">They were earnestly desired to aske the King par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, that so they might ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine their lives.</note> for the King was of nature full of clemency and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and if he would aske pardon of his Majesty, with confessing his offence, he should easily obtaine it. Hee answered with a valiant and bold courage, that it was not his part but the Kings to aske pardon of God for his fault, and that hee would never crave forgivenesse of that offence whereof he well knew himselfe,
<note place="margin">They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse.</note> and had God to witnesse that hee was cleare and innocent. Neverthelesse, he besought God to forgive the King this fault. So were these two excellent and famous men with halters fastened about their necks, throwne by the hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man from the ladder and hanged,
<note place="margin">They are hanged.</note> and therewithall also the man of straw made for figure of the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, was tyed fast and hanged with
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:36221:55"/>them, after a preposterous order of law, whereby the Admirall was first flaine and then condemned.</p>
            <p>But whereas, in a manner, in all Towns there were great slaughters cōmitted, yet was there none more horrible nor more out-ragious than the butcherly murder at <hi>Lions.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The most horrid and barbarous murder at <hi>Lions,</hi> and the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of it.</note> So soone as the letters from the Court were brought to <hi>Mandelot,</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the town: first, by a cryer &amp; trumpet he caused to be proclaimed, that al the professors of the <hi>Religion</hi> should appear presently before him at his house. They without all delay repaired to him. As soone as they were come, he commanded them all to suffer themselves to be led to prison by such officers as should be assigned them. They obeyed his word and followed the officers that led them. By reason of the great multitude, they sorted them into sundry prisons. Then <hi>Mandelot</hi> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the common executioner to be commanded in his name to take some to helpe him, and to kill those
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:36221:55"/>that were in prison.
<note place="margin">The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner refuses to kill those in prison.</note> The executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner answered, that hee used not to execute the law upon any but such as were condemned, and in publike and open places, and therefore wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him to seeke another slaughter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man if he would. <hi>Mandelot</hi> thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused by the executioner, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the garrison souldiers of the castle to do it.
<note place="margin">The soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise so horrid a villany, being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to slay those that lay suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants before them. The busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse is acted by butchers and water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> The souldiers answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that it was against their honour, to use weapon upon men bound and lying suppliant before them. If they had raised any rebellion, or had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended or provoked them, they said they would most readily have fought with them. Being thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused by them also, at the last he cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the matter to the water-men and butchers. Those fellowes being let into the prisons, went to it with chopping-knives &amp; butchers axes. Such as they found prostrate at their feet, pitiously holding up their hands to heaven, crying upon the mercy of God and men, they did for sport cut off their fingers and
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:36221:56"/>the toppes of their hands, and throughout the whole Towne was heard such a crie and lamentable howling of women and children, that innumerable people, even such as were zelously given even to the popish <hi>Religion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of cruelty.</note> did detest that cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, and judged that not men but outragious savage beasts in shape of men were entred into the prisons. It is well known, that a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of honest women in the Towne great with child, were so flighted with the horror of it, that they were deliver'd before their time. And out of the Court of the gaole, called the Archbishops prison,
<note place="margin">The bloud runs out of the gaole the next day warme and smoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king into the next streets, &amp; so to the River <hi>Seane.</hi>
               </note> the blood was seene in the broad day light, to the great abhorring and feare of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that beheld it, runne warme and smoaking into the next strets of the Town, and so down into the River of <hi>Seane.</hi> There was in that same Archbishops prison an aged man called <hi>Francis Collut,</hi> a merchant of cappes, and two young men his sonnes, whom hee had ever caused
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:36221:56"/>diligently to be taught and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed in <hi>Religion.</hi> When he saw the butchers come toward him with their Axes, he began to exhort his children not to refuse the death offered by Cod. For (said he) it is the perpetuall destinie of <hi>Religion,</hi> and that often such sacrifices do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide in Christian Churches, and Christians in al ages have ever been and for ever to the worlds end so shall be as sheepe among wolves, doves among hawkes, and sacrifices among Priests. Then the old father embraced his two young sons, and lying flat on the ground with them, crying aloud upō the mercy of God, was with many wounds both he and his sonnes slaughtered by those butchers: and long time afterward their three bodies had knit together yeelded a piteous spectacle to many that beheld them. In the meane time <hi>Mandelot</hi> in jest and scorne (as it seemed) caused to be proclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the cryer, that no man should commit any slaughter in
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:36221:57"/>the Towne,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mandelot</hi> in jest and scorne, caus'd to bee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim'd that the slaughters should cease; and the dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters of the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded, and from that time they cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed not to kill and slay.</note> and that if any would detect the doers of any such slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he would give him a hundred crownes in reward for his informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And from that time they cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed not to kill, to robbe and to spoyle. The next day after, which was the first day of September, the greatest part of the dead bodies were throwne into the River of <hi>Seane,</hi> and the rest of them, <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delot,</hi> to feed and glut his eyes and heart with bloud, caused to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by boat to the other side of the water, and there to be throwne downe upon the greene grasse neare unto the Abbey called <hi>Esne.</hi> There the people of <hi>Lions,</hi> specially the <hi>Italians,</hi> of whom by reason of the Mart there is great store in the Towne, satisfied their eyes a while, and did such spites as they could to these heapes of carcases, and so ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercised their cruelty not upon the living only, but also upon the dead. And there hapned one thing which for the abhominable cruelty is not
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:36221:57"/>to be omitted. There came to that spectacle certain Apothecaries,
<note place="margin">Abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rousnesse against the dead bodies.</note> and among those bodies they perceived some very fat ones, by and by they went to the butchers, and told them that they did use to make cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine speciall medicines of mans grease, and that they might make some profit thereof. Which as soone as the butchers understood, they ran to the heapes and chose out the fattest, and launced them with their knives and pulled out the fat, and sold it for money to the Apothecaries.</p>
            <p>While these things were doing at <hi>Lions,</hi> the King being informed that divers of the <hi>Religion</hi> had left their wives and children, and were fled out of the other Townes; and lurked some in the woods, &amp; some among their friends such as tooke pity on them, he practised with faire words to allure and call them home againe. He sent to every part messengers and letters, affirming that he was highly displeased
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:36221:58"/>with those slaughters and horrible butcheries,
<note place="margin">The King allures those that were fled, home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming his displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure with those slaughters, and that he would se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish them. Those that were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiled by the Kings speeches, returned home, was presently imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, cruelly tortured and slaine. For thirtie daies there was no end of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering thorow-out all <hi>France.</hi>
               </note> and that he would that such cruelty should be severely punished: and if the Admiral with a few of his confederates had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into any secret practize, it was no reason, that so many innocents should beare the punishment due to a few. Many sweetely beguiled with these words of the King and with the letters of the governours, retired home againe to their dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and houses, specially they of <hi>Rhoan, Diepe,</hi> and <hi>Tholouse.</hi> There were scant two dayes passed when they were againe commanded to prison, where they were all shut up. Then were murderers a new appointed of the most base and ras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call of the people, to torment them with all kind of torture, and then to slay them. And throughout the whole Realme of <hi>France</hi> for thirty dayes together there was no end of killing, slaying and robbing, so that there were about a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth thousand little babes, wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:36221:58"/>and children, that were well borne, that by reason hereof fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlesse and motherlesse live wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering and in beggery. About this time the King caused to be procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that such as had any office or place of charge, unlesse they would speedily returne to the Catholike, Apostolique and Romish Church, should give over those their tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall roomes: There was no Towne nor any so small a village or hamlet wherein all the professors of the <hi>Religion</hi> were not compelled either to go to Masse,
<note place="margin">All com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to Abjure the Protestant <hi>Religion,</hi> or be slaine. Many who abjured the <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward slain.</note> or presently to take the sword into their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somes: and in many places it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened that such as being amazed with the suddennesse of the matter had abjured their <hi>Religion,</hi> yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding were afterward slain.</p>
            <p>And while these things were still in doing, yet the King in the meane while sent abroad his letters and messages into al parts, and caused to be proclaimed with trumpet, that his pleasure was that the Edicts
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:36221:59"/>of Pacification should be observed:
<note place="margin">Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing all this, the King sends Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, that hee would keepe the Edicts of Pacifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that they should have li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of <hi>Religion.</hi> The King a few daies before sent Letters to the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces that the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall was slaine by the Duke of <hi>Guise,</hi> to his sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimes, that the trayterous Admirall was slaine by his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</note> and although they could not have freedome to use and exercise their <hi>Religion</hi> in open places, yet they should have liberty permitted them to retain and professe it within their own houses, and that no man should meddle with, or disturbe the goods and possessions of those of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the same King, which but few dayes before, had by letters di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to all the Governours of his Provinces, signified that his cousin the Admirall was slain by the Duke of <hi>Guise</hi> to his great sorrow, and that he himselfe was in great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, the same King, I say, now cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed it with sound of trumpet to be proclaimed that the trayterous and wicked Admirall was slaine by his will and commandement. Hee that in few dayes before had by new authority confirmed the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Religion</hi> permitted by his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts of Pacification, the same King did now not onely take from the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:36221:59"/>professors thereof, their Offices and Honours, but also prescribed them in precise forme of words a forme of abjuring and detesting their <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi> Which things lest any man should doubt of, we shall hereafter set down the very true copies of the said Letters, Edicts and Abjura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <div type="letters">
               <head>THE KINGS LETTERS, to the Governours of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> whereby he chargeth those of the House of <hi>Guise,</hi> for the murder committed upon the Admirals person, and for the sedition which happened at <hi>Paris,</hi> and commandeth that the Edict of Pacification should be kept and retained.</head>
               <div type="letter">
                  <p>
                     <hi>COusin, you have perceived what I wrote unto you yesterday, concerning my cousin the Admirals wounding, and how ready I was to do my endevour to search out the truth
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:36221:60"/>of the deed, and to punish it, wherein nothing was left undone or forgotten. But it hapned since, that they of the House of Guise, and other Lords and Gentlemen their adherents (whereof there be no small number in this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) when they certainly knew that the Admirals friends would proceed to the revenge of his hurt, &amp; because they were suspected to be the authors thereof, were so stirred up this last night, that a great and lamentable sedition arose thereof, insomuch that the guard by me appointed for his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence about his house, was set upon and he himselfe with certaine of his Gentlemen slain, and havock of other made in divers places of the Citie, which was handled with such a rage, that I could not use the remedy that I would, but had much ado to employ my Guards and other defence for the safety of my selfe and my brethren within the Castle of Louure, to give order hereafter for the appeasing of this sedition, which is at this houre well appeased, thanks be to God, and
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:36221:60"/>came to passe by a particular and private quarrell of long time foster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed betwixt those two Houses. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, when I fore-saw that there would succeed some mischievous purpose, I did what I could possibly to appease it, as all men know. And yet hereby the Edict of Pacification is not bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, which I will to be kept as strait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as ever it was, as I have given to understand in all places thorow-out my Realme. And because it is great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be feared, that such an execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion might stir up my subjects, one against another, and cause great murders thorow the Cities of my Realme, whereby I should be greatly grieved, I pray you cause to be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished and understood in all places of your Government, that every person abide and continue in the safegard of his owne house, and to take no wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons in hand, nor one to hurt another upon paine of death: commanding them to keepe and diligently to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve our Edict of Pacification. And to make the offenders and resisters,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:36221:61"/>and such as would disobey and break our will, to be punished: You shall assemble out of hand as great force as you can, as well of your friends as of them that be appointed by me and of others, advertising the Captaines of Castles and Cities in your go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, to take heed to the safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard and preservation of the said places, so that no fault ensue on their behalf, advertising me also so soon as you can, what order you have given herein, and how all things have pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed within the circuit of your Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. Hereupon I pray God to keepe you, Cousin, in his holy safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>At Paris</hi>
                        <date>
                           <hi>the</hi> 24. <hi>of August.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Signed</hi> CHARLES, <hi>and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath,</hi> BRULARD.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <head>ANOTHER LETTER FROM the King to the Lord of <hi>Prye,</hi> his Lieutenant generall in <hi>Touraine,</hi> upon the same matter that the former Letter was.</head>
                  <p>MOnsieur de Prye, <hi>you have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood how my Cousin the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:36221:61"/>Admirall was hurt the last day, and in what readinesse I was to doe as much as in mee lay, for the triall of the fact, and to cause so great and speedy justice to bee done as should be an example throughout all my Realme, wherein nothing was omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Since it is so happened, that my Cousins of the House of Guise, and other Lords and Gentlemen their adherents, which are no small party in this town, as all men know, having gotten certaine intelligence that the friends of my said Cousin, the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, intended to pursue and execute upon them the revenge of this hurt, for that they had them in suspition to be the cause and occasion thereof, have made such a stir this night past, that among them on both parts hath been raised a great and lamentable tumult: the Guard that was set a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Lord Admirals house, was distressed, himselfe slaine in his house with divers other Gentlemen, as also great slaughter hath been made of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in sundry places &amp; quarters of
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:36221:62"/>this Towne; which hath been done with such fury, that it was impossible for me to give such remedy as was to be wished, I having enough to doe to employ my Guard and other forces to keep my selfe in safety in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle of Louure, to the end to give or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for the appeasing of the whole up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roare, which at this houre (thankes be to God) is well quenched, for that the same happened by the particular quarrell that hath of long time been between those two Houses, wherof al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes having some doubt that some unhappy effect would ensue, I have (as is well knowne to all men) before this time done all that I could for to appease it, nothing in this last fact tending to the breach of my Edict of Pacification, which contrariwise I will in all things to be maintained, as at any time heretofore, as I doe give it to understand thorow-out my Realme. And for asmuch as it is greatly to be feared that this may stir up and cause my subjects to rise one against another, and to commit
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:36221:62"/>great slaughters in the Towns of my Realme, whereof I should be marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lously sory, I pray you that immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately upon the receipt hereof, ye cause to be published and given to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand in al places of your charge, that every man as wel in town as in coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, remaine in rest and surety in his house, and do not take armes one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst another, on pain of death: And that more diligently than at any time heretofore, ye cause the last E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict of Pacification to be kept, and carefully maintained and observed to the intent above-said, and to punish such as shall do to the contrary, and to take into safe custody all such as shall rise and disobey our pleasure, yee shall immediately assemble all the strength that yee are able, as well of your friends being of Our allowance, as others, advertising the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and Captains of Townes and Castles within your charge, that they take good heed to the surety and safe keeping of their peeces, in such sort as there ensue no default, enforming
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:36221:63"/>me with speed of such order as you shall take therein, and how all things shall proceed within the compasse of your authority. I have here with me my brother the King of Navar, and my Cousin the Prince of Conde, to take such hap as my selfe. I pray the Creator,</hi> Monsieur de Prie, <hi>to hold you in His holy safegard.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>From Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi>
                        <date>
                           <hi>this</hi> 24. <hi>of August.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Thus signed</hi> CHARLES, <hi>and underneath</hi> PINART.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>These Letters are all of one argument as the former be, and written all in one forme, and all one day to <hi>Monsieur de Prie</hi> the Lieutenant of Touraine.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <head>THE KINGS LETTERS to the Officers of Burges, upon the same matter that the former were.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>OƲr loving and faithfull, we doubt not but by this time you know of the sedition which to our great grief happened in Paris a few dayes since, wherein my Cousin the Admirall,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:36221:63"/>and certaine others of his side were slaine, and a great murder commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon diverse in many places of this City. And lest the newes thereof should change the quiet estate, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Burges hath hitherto been main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained since the Edict of Pacificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if remedy were not fore-seene, it is the cause that we writ this Letter presently unto you, whereby we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and expresly ordain that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of you according to his charge do see that no commotion or insurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction be against the inhabitants of the said City, nor that no murder be committed, as it is to be feared, by those that pretend to breake the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict of Pacification, and thereby would execute a revenge of their long and private grudge, to our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible vexation and anguish of mind. For this cause it is your part to give to understand and publish thorow-out that City of ours, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places pertaining to it, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one should quietly and peaceably keepe their houses, without taking
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:36221:64"/>weapons in hand, and offending one the other, upon paine of death, and well and diligently to keepe our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict of Pacification. And if any go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to contrary this Our intent and mind, to cause them to be punished and rigorously chastised by penalties imposed on such offendours in Our Ordinances, having a watchfull and diligent eye to the safeguard of that Our City, in such sort that no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience arise in your service to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Ʋs, as you would have Ʋs to know, that you are Our loyall and obedient subjects.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Given at Paris <date>the 27. day of August, 1572.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Thus Signed,</hi> CHARLES, <hi>and below,</hi> De neuf-ville.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:36221:64"/>
                  <head>A LETTER OF THE Treasurer of the Leagues of the Switzers, written by the Kings commandement unto the said Leagues of the same argument that the former Letters were.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>NOble Seigniours, Monsieur</hi> de la Fontaine, <hi>Ambassadour for the King your assured and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Friend and Confederate, and I his Treasurer in this Countrey, having commandement of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty to communicate with you, as with them whom hee accompteth his chiefe and sure Friends, of a chance which lately happened in the City of Paris, his owne persen and Court then being there, whereof he received so much more griefe and displeasure, because it befell on such a time as he least feared, or looked for such a thing. The matter is this. On the</hi> 27. <hi>day of August last, the Admirall as he went from Louure, was with an Harquebuze shot
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:36221:65"/>hurt in the hand and arme, whereof when his Majesty was advertised, he commanded incontinent that search and punishment were had of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendor, and the authours of such a mischiefe: whereunto, when he had readily laid his hand by his Officers, and committed the inhabitants of the house, where the harquebuze was shot, to prison, they which were the first cause of the mischief (as it may easily be presupposed) because they would prevent the inquisition there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, heaping one transgression upon another, on the</hi> 23. <hi>and</hi> 24. <hi>of the said moneth assembled a great troop of people in the night, and moved the people of Paris to a very great sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who in a rage set upon the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirals lodging, and enforcing the Guard which his Majesty had set for the Admirals surety and keeping, slew him with certain other Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in his company, as the like also was committed upon others in the City, the matter growing in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry same instant to such an outrage
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:36221:65"/>and commotion, that whereas his Majesty had thought to provide re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy for appeasing thereof, hee had much a doe with all his Guards to keep his house at Louure, where he lodged with the two Queens, his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Spouse, the Lords his brethren, the King of Navarre and other Princes. Thinke therefore yee Noble Seigniours, in what a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity this young and couragious King now standeth, who, as a man may say, hath held in his hand thorns in stead of a Scepter ever since his comming to the Crown, for the great troubles which have almost ever since been in his Realme, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the good and wise counsel and assistance of the Queene his mother, and the Lords his brethren, thought to enjoy and establish a more sure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose in his Realme, and a more hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie government for himselfe and his subjects, after hee had taken away (as he thought) all occasions of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentions amongst his subjects, by the meanes of his Edicts of Pacificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:36221:66"/>and of the marriage of the King of Navarre to the Lady his sister, and the Prince of Conde to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame</hi> de Nevers. <hi>Besides all this, to the intent nothing should be left undone that might serve for the quieting of all things, and especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for the Admirals safeguard; his Majesty, as every man knoweth, hath done his endevour to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most, to appease and reconcile his principall and most dangerous ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies unto him. And so God the true Judge of the Kings Majesties good and pure intent, brought to passe, that the peoples rage being quieted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a few houres, every one went home to his house, and the King had speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all regard to nothing more than to see nothing attempted or innovated contrary to his Edicts of Pacificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the repose of his subjects, as well of the one</hi> Religion, <hi>as of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And for that purpose hath sent to diverse of his Governours and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers in his Provinces, to looke dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to the observing of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:36221:66"/>with expresse commandement to hold their hands there, that every one might perceive that the chance at Paris happened for some private quarrell, and not for any purpose to alter his Edicts, which his Majesty will in no wise suffer. Which is the principall thing, Noble Seigniours, that his Majesty hath commanded us on his part to assure you, and to let you understand the dangers that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend over him and his neighbours, not so much for this sedition, for he trusteth in God that shall grow no further, and his Majesty will keepe his Realme in as good repose as it hath been since his last Edict of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cification, but for the great muster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and assembling men of warre in many places, especially in the Low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countreys, where it is yet uncertaine on which side God will give the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, nor whether the conquerour will employ his force, after his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest. Wherefore his Majesty pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth you, continuing the good love and intelligence which hath alwayes
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:36221:67"/>been betwixt the Crowne of France and his allied and confederate friends the Seigniours of the Leagues, to have good regard to him, and his Realme, in case that need shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, as hee will have to you and your prosperous estate, if it be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site, employing in the meane while your great and singular wisdome to the preservation of the union of the Nation in League, which is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meanes to make you, not only able to send succour to your friends, but also maintaine your selves in estima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that you may be a terrour to your neighbours, how great soever they be, his Majesty promising you in all occurrents as much friendship, favour and assictance, as you can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire, and to be as entire and perfect a friend, as ever your nation had any.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb n="127" facs="tcp:36221:67"/>
            <head>A DECLARATION OF the King, concerning the occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Admirals death and his adherents and complices, hapned in the City of Paris the 24. of August 1572.</head>
            <head type="sub">Imprinted at Paris by <hi>John Dallier</hi> Stationer, dwelling on Saint <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaels</hi> bridge, at the signe of the white Rose: By the Kings Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence.</head>
            <p>BY THE King,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>HIS Majesty desiring to have all Seigniours, Gentlemen, and other his subjects, understand the cause of the murder of the Admirall and his adherents and complices, which lately happened in this City of Paris the</hi> 24. <hi>day of this present moneth of August, lest the said deed should be otherwise disguised and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported than it was indeed: His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty therefore declareth that which was done, was by his expresse com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:36221:68"/>and for no cause of</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, <hi>nor breaking his Edicts of Pacification, which he alwayes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, and still mindeth and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to observe and keepe: yea, it was rather done to withstand and prevent a most detestable and cursed conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy begun by the said Admirall the chiefe Captaine thereof, and his said adherents and complices, against the Kings person, his estate, the Queene his mother, and the Princes his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, the King of Navarre, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Lords about him. Wherefore his Majesty by this Declaration &amp; Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance giveth to understand to all Gentlemen and others of the</hi> Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>which they pretend reformed, that he mindeth and purposeth that they shall live under his protection, with their wives and children in their houses, in as much safoguard as they did before, following th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nefit of the former Edicts of Pacification, most expresly commanding and ordaining, that all Governours and Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants generall in every of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:36221:68"/>and Provinces, and other Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stices and Officers, to whom it apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth, do not attempt, nor suffer to be attempted any thing in what sort soever, upon the persons and goods of them of the</hi> Religion, <hi>their wives, children, and families, on paine of death to be inflicted on those that shall be found faulty and culpable in this behalfe. And neverthelesse to withstand the troubles, slanders, suspitions, and defiances that may come by Sermons and assemblies, as well in the house of the said Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, as in other places, as it is suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered by the said Edicts of Pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: it is expressely forbidden, and inhibited by his Majesty to all Gentlemen and others of the said</hi> Religion, <hi>to have no assemblies for any cause at all, untill his Majesty hath provided and appointed other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise for the tranquillity of his Realme, upon paint of disobedience and confiscation of body and goods. It is also expressely forbidden under the paine aforesaid, that for the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:36221:69"/>foresaid occasions, none shall take or retain any prisoners, or take ransome of them, and that incontinently they certifie the Governours of every Province, and the Lieutenant Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, of the name and quality of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry such prisoner, whom his Majesty hath appointed shall be released and set at liberty, except they be of the chiefe of the late conspiracy, or such as have made some practise or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vise for them, or had intelligence thereof: and they shall advertise his Majesty of such, to know his further pleasure. It is also ordained, that from hence-forth none shall take or arrest any prisoner for that cause, without his Majesties commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or his Officers, nor that none be suffered to roame abroad in the fields, to take up dogs, Cattel, Beefes, Kine, or other beasts, goods, fruits, graine, nor any thing else, nor to hurt the labourers by word or deed, but to let them alone about their work and calling, in peace and safety.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>At Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 28. <hi>of August.</hi> 1572.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:36221:69"/>
                  <hi>Signed,</hi> CHARLES, <hi>and underneath</hi> FIZES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>THE KINGS LETTERS to the Officers of Burges, of the same argument that the former Declaration was.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>OƲR trusty and well beloved, We considering that under the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of the death of the Admirall, and his adherents and complices, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Gentlemen, and others our sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, professing the</hi> Religion <hi>called Reformed, might rise and assemble together to the prejudice and hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the tranquillity which we have alwayes desired should be in our Realme, the doing of the said murder being counterfeited and given out o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise than it was. We have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore made a Declaration and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, which we send you, willing you to publish the same incontinent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by sound of Trumpet, and setting the same up in such places of your Jurisdiction, where cryes and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:36221:70"/>are usually made, to the end that every one might know it. And although we have alwayes been diligent observers of our Edicts of Pacification; yet seeing the troubles and seditions which might arise a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst our subjects by the occasion of the said murder, as wel of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall as of his companions, we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you, and ordaine, that you par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly forbid the principals of the</hi> Religion, <hi>pretended reformed, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your Jurisdiction, that they have no Sermons nor assemblies either in their houses, or in any other places, to take away all doubt and suspition which might be conceived against them. And likewise that you adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise such as dwel in the Cities of your Jurisdiction, what you judge meet to be done, to the intent they might in this point follow Our mind, and keep them quiet in their houses, as they may do by the benefit of our Edict of Pacification, and there they shall be under Our protection and safeguard: but if they will not so retire them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:36221:70"/>after you have given them warning, then shall you set on them with all strength and force, as wel by the Provosts of the Marishals and their Archers, as others which you can gather together by Bell-ringing or otherwise, so that you hew them all to peeces as enemies to Our Crowne. Besides, what commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments soever we have sent by word of mouth, either to you, or others in Our Realme, when we were in feare, upon just occasion, knowing the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiracy that the Admirall had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun of some mischance that might fall unto us, we have and do revoke, willing you and others that no such thing be executed, for such is Our pleasure.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Given at Paris</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 30. <hi>of August,</hi> 1572.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thus signed</hi> CHARLES, <hi>and underneath,</hi> De Neuf-ville.</signed>
               <hi>Published in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="remembrances">
            <pb n="134" facs="tcp:36221:71"/>
            <head>REMEMBRANCES AND Instructions sent by the King to the Count of Charny, his Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Lieutenant in Burgundy, of the same argument.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THe King considering the commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion lately happened in Paris, wherein the Lord Admirall</hi> Chasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion <hi>with other Gentlemen of his side were slaine, because they had mischi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vously conspired to set upon the Kings Majesties person, the Queene his mother, the Princes his brethren, the King of Navarre, and other Princes and Lords near about them, and upon his estate: and lest they of the</hi> Religion <hi>called reformed, not knowing the true causes of the said rebellion, should arise and put themselves in armes as they have done in the troubles that be passed, and devise new practises and fetches against the weale of his Majesty and tranquillity of his Realme, if hee should not cause the truth of the
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:36221:71"/>matter to be knowne to all Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and others his subjects of the same religion how it passed, and what his pleasure and mind is in their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfes. And thinking that for remedy hereof, it is very needfull for the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of the Provinces in his Realme to go round about their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments: for this occasion he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth that the Count of Charny great Esquire of France, and his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Lieutenant General for the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of Burgundy, shall go di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently thorow all Cities and places of the said Government, and as he arriveth in every place, he shall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vise the best wayes that he can to make peace, union and quietnesse a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the Kings subjects, aswell of the one Religion as of the other. And to bring it the better about, he shall gently call before him in open or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate place, as he shall see best cause for his Majesties service herein, the Gentlemen of the Places, and the Burgesses of the Cities of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, that be of the</hi> Religion,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:36221:72"/>
               <hi>and shal declare unto them, and cause them to understand the truth of the said commotion, lest any have misre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported it to them, otherwise than it was indeed. And shall tell them, that under the colour of the Lord Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals hurt, wherefore his Majesty would have caused justice to be done according to the good order that he had appointed, the said Admirall and Gentlemen of his</hi> Religion <hi>which were in the City with him, without looking for the execution of the said Justice, had made a mischievous, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy, and detestable conspiracy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Kings Majesties person, the Queen his mother, the Lords his brethren, the King of Navarre, and other Princes and Lords with them, and against the whole Estate, even as certain of the chiefe and adherents of the said conspiracy (acknowledging their fault) have confessed. Wherfore his Majesty was constrained (to his great griefe) to resist and prevent so mischievous, pernicious and abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable a purpose. And that which hee
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:36221:72"/>suffered to bee done on Sunday, the</hi> 24. <hi>of August, upon the Admirall and his complices, was not for any</hi> Religion, <hi>nor to goe against the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict of Pacification, hee intending neverthelesse that they of the</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion <hi>should still live and abide in all liberty and safety, with their wives, children and families in their houses, as he hath and will maintain them, if they be content to live quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly under his obedience as he desireth. For the which cause he willeth, that the Count</hi> Charny <hi>shall offer and give to them his Letters of safeguard in good and authentick forme, which shall be of as good force and vertue, as if they should come or be taken from his owne Majesty: and by the authority of them they shall be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served from all wrongs, violences, and oppressions: enjoyning and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding most expressely all his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique subjects, whosoever they are, to attempt nothing, upon the persons, goods, or families of any of the</hi> Religion <hi>which kept them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:36221:73"/>quietly in their houses, on pain of death. And if any be so rash, or evill advised, to do against this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, or to violate the safegard promised, his Majesty willeth that ready and rigorous punishment be done, to the intent that their exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may serve to hold in others not to do the like: which is the true and only means of assurance that his Majesty can give to them of the</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, <hi>with his word and promise which he giveth them to be their good and benigne Prince, protector &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>server of them, and of all that touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them, so long as they live and continue under his obedience with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doing or enterprising any thing against his will and service. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause his Majesty hath often known that the enterprises and consultations taken in hand by them of the</hi> Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>against his service, have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded amongst them at assemblies at Sermons, which Gentlemen had liberty to cause to be made in their houses and Lordships: therefore my
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:36221:73"/>Lord of</hi> Charnye <hi>shall particularly give to understand to Gentlemen which were wont to have such Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, that his Majesty in considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that nothing hath more moved and set on the Catholiques against those of the</hi> Religion, <hi>than such prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings &amp; assemblies, and if they cōti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue it is certain that it wilbe a cause to encrease and maintaine the said commotions, desireth that they should cause them to cease off untill he hath otherwise provided and appointed, and that they apply themselves here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, as a thing greatly serving the effect of his intention, which is gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to bring his said subjects to a true and perfect amity, union and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord one with another, committing all divisions and partialities to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livion. And because this may secome hard at the beginning, my Lord of</hi> Charny <hi>shall cause it to be faire and gently spoken to them, lest they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into some strange conjecture, or suspition. For so his said Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie would proceed in all true
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:36221:74"/>sincerity towards them which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme themselves to his will and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, wherein he exhorteth them to live, with all the best perswasions that he can, and shall assure them, in so doing, to be surely maintained and preserved as his other subjects the Catholiques, as his Majesty would that he should do. And to the intent his said subjects the Catholiques should know how to use and behave themselves herein, my L. of</hi> Charny <hi>shal tel them that his Majesties plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure neither is nor hath bin, that any wrong or oppression should be done to them of the said</hi> Religion, <hi>which like good and loyall subjects will gently keepe themselves under his obedience. Declaring unto the said Catholikes, that if they forget themselves, and hurt those of the</hi> Religion, <hi>which in such sort behave them selves toward his Majesty, and those also which for that end have received of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, or of my Lord of</hi> Charny, <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of safe-conduct, hee will cause them to be punished and chastised in
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:36221:74"/>the field, as transgressors of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, without any hope of grace, pardon, or remission. Which the said Lord of</hi> Charny <hi>shall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse and declare unto them, with as plaine words as is possible, and cause it also to be as straightly executed. And after that following his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties intent, he hath pacified them by this meanes, which is the way that his Majesty best liketh of, and sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the direction to assure a tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity between the subjects, and to set some assurance betwixt the one and the other, such as shall conforme themselves herein to his said Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties will, he will comfort, and make them the best and most gentle enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment that he possibly can. But if any of the</hi> Religion <hi>become selfe-wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and stubborne to his Majesty, without having regard to his said warnings, and shal assemble in armes together, making practises and devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses against the weale of his service: then the Lord of</hi> Charny <hi>shall runne upon them, and hew them in pieces
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:36221:75"/>before they have power to fortifie themselves and joyne together. And therefore he shall assemble as much force as he can, as well of the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as of other men of warre, Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, Foot-men of the garrisons, and inhabitants of the Catholikes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Cities of his Government, and shal besiege them which hold and make themselves strong in Cities a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout of his Government, so that the victory and authority may remaine in his Majesty.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>At</hi> Paris <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 30. <hi>of August</hi> 1572.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Signed</hi> CHARLES: <hi>and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath</hi> BRULARD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>THE KINGS LETTERS to the Lord of <hi>Gwich,</hi> whereby it may plainely bee perceived, how they would search out all them of the <hi>Religion</hi> which had any charge in hand during the troubles.</head>
            <p>MY L. <hi>of</hi> Gwich, <hi>I understand that the three brethren</hi> Dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonels,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:36221:75"/>
               <hi>and one</hi> Porcher, <hi>the host at the signe of the Adventure,</hi> Mosso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, Crispine, <hi>and Captain</hi> Grise, <hi>which were the principall of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in</hi> Burgundy, <hi>and were the cause of the taking and recovering of the City of</hi> Mascon <hi>in the late troubles, and of all the decay which happened in that Countrey, be kept prisoners in</hi> Mascon. <hi>And because I understand they hope to escape out by ransome (which I would in no wise should bee done) I ordain and command that you keep them safe, for as much as I hope by their means to discover a great many things, which greatly touch the weale of my ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. And if there be any other priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the new</hi> Religion <hi>in</hi> Mascon, <hi>which have been factions, you shall likewise keepe thē so that they escape not by paying rāsome, for I would not for any thing in the world that there should be taking of rāsome among my subjects. And thus my L. of</hi> Gwich <hi>I pray God keepe you in his holy tuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Written at</hi> Paris <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 24. <hi>of
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:36221:76"/>Septemb.</hi> 1572.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>signed</hi> CHARLES, <hi>and underneath,</hi> BRULARD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>THE KINGS LETTERS to <hi>Monsieur de Gordes</hi> his Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant generall in <hi>Daulphine,</hi> wherein he sendeth him word, that the best proofe of his doings is the accusations and complaints of them of the <hi>Religion</hi> against him, whereunto he should have care to answer.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>M.</hi> De Gordes, <hi>by your Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the first of this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, I perceived the order which you appointed in your Government since the advertisement which you had of the execution of the Admirall and his adherents: and since I am sure you forgot nothing which you thought might serve for your assurance of those places whereof you had occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to doubt. And to the intent you should have the more means to make your selfe knowne, I have prepared that the souldiers of</hi> Corsica, <hi>which I
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:36221:76"/>had appointed to go into</hi> Province, <hi>should returne to you, and thereupon have written to my Cousin, the</hi> Count <hi>of</hi> Tende, <hi>who will not faile to send them unto you, for as much as there is no need of them now in that Countrey. Hee should also send you word of the time of their departing, to the end that you might have lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure to provide to receive them, and appoint their places where they should bee in garrison. I have seene that which you writ to me concerning the continuall payment in</hi> Daulphine, <hi>what is due for the last yeare, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I will advise of the state of my fines the meanes that may be, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording thereunto there shall be no fault, but they shall be provided for. For the reparation of the Bridge of</hi> Grenoble, <hi>they of the same place must devise the means wherein they should best help themselves therein, and when they have advertised me, I will appoint them necessary provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion. Touching the souldiers appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the Baron of</hi> Adresse, <hi>because
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:36221:77"/>the occasion why I appointed them to be levied now ceaseth, I have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to him to send them back and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misse them again: wherefore there is no need to make provision for their maintenance, nor likewise to tell you any thing else concerning the answers which you have made to the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances which they of the</hi> Religion <hi>have presented against you. For your doings are well known and plain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, and thereupon I will take no better proofe than their accusation. Wherefore you shall put your selfe to no more pain on that side. Moreover, I have herewith sent you a copy of the declaration which I made of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirals death and his adherents, and made to be understood that it should be observed and followed, and that all murders, sackings, and violences should cease. Neverthelesse I have heard complaints of diverse places that such extraordinary waies conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, which is a thing, that doth much displease me. By the meanes whereof I advise you, in doing this charge
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:36221:77"/>once againe put unto you, that you give order thorow-out your Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to cause all hostility, force, and violence to cease, and that the said Declaration be straightly observed and kept, with punishing those that withstand, so rigorously, that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstration thereof may serve for an example, seeing my intent is that they should be punished as behoveth, and to marke them which wincke or dissemble thereat. This present Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter shall serve also for an advise of the receipt of those Letters which you wrote the fifth of this present, whereby you send me word, that you received no message by word of mouth from me, but only Letters of the</hi> 22, 24, <hi>and</hi> 28, <hi>of the moneth past, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of put your selfe to no further paine, for that charge was onely for such as then were neare about me, which is all that I have at this time to say unto you. Praying hereupon the Creator to keepe you in his holy and worthy tuition.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Written at</hi> Paris <date>
                     <hi>the fourth day of September.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:36221:78"/>
                  <hi>Signed,</hi> CHARLES, <hi>and beneath</hi> FIZES, <hi>and above,</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>
               <hi>To M.</hi> de Gordes, <hi>Knight.</hi>
            </trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>THE KINGS LETTERS to the Duke of <hi>Guise,</hi> his Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant generall in <hi>Champaigne,</hi> and in <hi>Prye.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>COusin, although in all my former Letters I have given you to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand well enough how much I desire that all my subjects, as well of the Nobility as others which professe the new</hi> Religion, <hi>and quietly use themselves in your Government, should by you be maintained and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served in all surety under my prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and safeguard, without giving them any hinderance by trouble in their persons, goods, and families: yet neverthelesse I have been advertised that in certain places of my Realme there have been many sackings and pillings done by such as dwell in the houses of them of the said new</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, <hi>as well in the fields as in the
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:36221:78"/>Cities, under colour of the commoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which happened in my City of</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris <hi>the</hi> 24. <hi>day of August last, a thing beyond all measure displeasant and disagreeable unto mee, and for the which I would have provision &amp; remedy. Wherefore I pray you, Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sin, that above all things, as you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire that I should know the good affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction you beare to the good weale of my service, you take that matter next your heart, to preserve and maintaine within your Government, according to that which I have so plainly told and written to you here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, that all such of the new</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion <hi>which behave themselves quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, take no wrong or violence, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it bee for the preservation of their goods or persons, no more than to my Catholike subjects. And where any wrong or out-rage shall be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them against my will, as I have before declared, so do I now by these presents declare; I will and intend that you shal make some evident and notorious punishment of such as are
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:36221:79"/>herein culpable, so that their corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction may serve for an example of all other, that I may see my self through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obeyed herein as I would be, and my cōmandements received amongst all my subjects in another sort than they have been heretofore. Assuring you cousin, that the best newes that I shall receive from you, shall be to heare say that you chastise those wel, of whom I am disobeyed. And thus Cousin, I pray God to keep you in his holy tuition.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Written from</hi> Paris <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 28. <hi>of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember,</hi> 1572.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Signed</hi> CHARLES: <hi>And underneath</hi> BRULART.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="remembrances">
            <head>REMEMBRANCES SENT BY the King to all Governours, and Lieutenants of his Provinces, to put out and remove all those of the <hi>Religion</hi> from their estates and charges, although they would abjure the same, saving such as have but smal estates and offices, to whom his Majesty permitteth continuance, on con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:36221:79"/>that they abjure the said <hi>Religion</hi> according to the forme of Abjuration sent for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THe King considering how much his Officers and Magistrates of Justice, and such as have the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistration and dealing of his Fines and payments, which be of the new</hi> Religion, <hi>are suspect and hated, and put his Catholike subjects in great mistrust if they should presently exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise their offices after these fresh com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motiōs: therfore lest the people should thereby be brought to a new occasion of stirre, and they of the new</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion <hi>bee in danger or hazard of their owne persons, although they would abjure their said new</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, <hi>and professe the Holy Faith and Catholique Religion of Rome: His Majestie desiring to avoyd the new mischiefes and troubles which may come, hath advised to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the said Officers from the exercise of the said Offices, untill he
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:36221:80"/>shall otherwise appoint. And yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthelesse, in the meane while, if the said Officers bee obedient unto his will, and live quietly in their houses, without attempting, practising, or taking any thing in hand against his service, they shal receive their wages, and they that will resigne their said Offices to Catholique persons, and come to his Majesty, shall be honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably provided for. And as touching other small Offices without wages, which cannot be troublesome, as No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries, Sergeants, and such where the Officers have none authority, which cannot be so odious nor mistrustfull to the people as the other; his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty is advised, that such small Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers which will abjure the said new</hi> Religion, <hi>and professe the faith Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike, Apostolike, and Romish, and therein live continually hereafter, shall continue in the exercise and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying of their estates: but they that will continue in their new opinion, shall depart from their Offices, untill his Majesty hath otherwise provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:36221:80"/>And this is for the great mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe and inconvenience that may betide them, if they should exercise their said estates, because of the great mistrust and suspition which the Catholikes have conceived of them of the new</hi> Religion. <hi>Neverthelesse his Majesty well considering that the most part of the said officers have none other way to live, but the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise of their said offices, willeth that they shall be in choyse to resigne to Catholique and capable persons, and then to come to him for that effect, and he will grant them the greatest favour and moderation of his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sury that is possible. The which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution and pleasure of his Majesty he willeth to be declared to the said officers of the new pretended opinion as well by Governours and Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants generall of his Provinces, as by them of his courts of Parliament, of the Chamber of his accompts, of the Court of his Aydes, them of his great Councell, of the Treasury of</hi> France, <hi>the Generals of his Fines,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:36221:81"/>his Baylifes, Seneshals, Provosts, Judges, or their Lieutenants, and every one of them as shall appertain. And to this intent his Majesty wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth and intendeth that every one of them in their calling shal send parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly &amp; apart for every of the said officers of the new</hi> Religion, <hi>which be of their incorporation, charge and Jurisdiction, and shal admonish them in this behalf to conform themselves to his Majesties mind: and if any of them in authority, because of their said estates, will returne to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some of the Catholique and Romish Church, it shall be said to them that his Majesty liketh very wel of it, and that he taketh a great and singular affection therin, and that it shal give him the greater assurance and credit of their good will, and that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty will not bar them from his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice hereafter, but will provide for them as their behaviour shall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve. And notwithstanding, for the reasons above-said, hee willeth that they shall cease from the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:36221:81"/>of their estates and offices, untill he otherwise appointeth. And because that in many places of the Realme they have proceeded by way of sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing the goods of them of the new</hi> Religion <hi>which be dead or absent, and hide themselves: and sometimes of those which be in their owne hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, although his Majesty gave to understand by his Declaration of the</hi> 28. <hi>of August last, that hee would and intended that they of the new</hi> Religion <hi>should enjoy their goods, neverthelesse to the intent there should be no doubt of his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, and that no mistrust might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rise thereupon, he declareth, willeth, and intendeth againe, that according to his Declaration of the</hi> 28. <hi>of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust, they of the new</hi> Religion <hi>which be living, whether they be present or absent, and bee not culpable or charged with the last conspiration, or to have attempted against his Majesty or his Estate, since his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict of Pacification, shall be restored to their houses, and put in possession
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:36221:82"/>of all and singular their goods move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able or unmoveable. And that the widowes and heires of them that be dead, may and shal succeed them, and apprehend all and singular their goods, and that they shall be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in them, and kept under the protection and safeguard of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, so that no hurt shall be done or said unto them in any manner of wayes or sort. Willing for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose that all necessary surety shall be given them, and that all Officers, Magistrates, Majors and others, which have publique charge, shall maine them in all safety, forbidding all persons of what estate, quality or condition soever they be, not to hurt them in person or goods upon pain of death. And neverthelesse his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty willeth, that they of the new O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion shall submit themselves, and promise upon paine to be declared re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels and traitors to his Majesty, that they shall hereafter live under his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience without attempting any thing to the contrary, or taking their
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:36221:82"/>parts that doe attempt against his Majesty and estate, or things against his Ordinances, and to acknowledge none but his Majesty or such as hee shall appoint under him to have au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to command them. And if they know any that shall enterprise against his Majesty and service, to reveale them incontinent to him and his Officers, as good and faithfull subjects. And to take way all doubt and suspition, as well from the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility as others, because that in the Declaration of the</hi> 24. <hi>of the last moneth, these words are contained,</hi> (Except they be those of the chief, which had commandement for those of the new Opinion, or those which made practises and devises for them, or those which might have had intelligence of the said conspiracy.) <hi>His Majesty decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that he meaneth not of things done and past during the troubles which were before the Edict of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cification in August</hi> 1570. <hi>and that there shall be no inquisition thereof,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:36221:83"/>and none shal be troubled in goods or person therefore (but for that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect they shall enjoy the benefit of the Edict of Pacification) but that the said words extend only to those which be found to be guilty or acces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary to the last conspiracy done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst his Majesty and Estate, and that others which are imprisoned, shal be set at liberty. And as touching them which will make profession of their faith, and return to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Religion, his Majesty desireth that his Governours and officers shal excite and comfort them as much as they can, to that effect, and execution of that good will: and that their friends and kinsfolkes should also be exhorted to do the like for their part. And if any should hurt them in goods or body, his Majesty willeth ready and speedy execution to be done on them. And to the intent that they may follow the forme which hath bin kept, in professing the faith which they do make that returne to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postolique and Romish Church, there
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:36221:83"/>is sent herewith a memory thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From</hi> Paris <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 22. <hi>day of Septemb.</hi> 1572.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Signed</hi> CHARLES, <hi>and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath</hi> PINART.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="form">
            <head>THE FORME OF ABJU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Heresie, and confession of faith, which they which have swarved from the Faith, and pretend to be received into the Church, ought to make.</head>
            <head type="sub">THIS IS THE ABJƲ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration which they caused al of the <hi>Religion</hi> to make in <hi>France,</hi> to save their lives. Printed at <hi>Paris</hi> by <hi>Nicolas Roffet,</hi> dwelling in the new street of our Lady, at the sign of the Mower: With the Kings Privilege.</head>
            <p>FIrst, they which have swarved from the Faith, and desire to returne into the compasse of our holy Mother Church, ought to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent themselves to their Curates or Vicars to bee instructed of that which they ought to do: that done,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:36221:84"/>they shall be sent unto the reverend Bishop of the Dioces, or his Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour, or Officiall, to make the said Abjuration and Confession in manner and forme following.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I. N.</hi> Borne at, &amp;c. in the Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of, &amp;c. and dwelling, &amp;c. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging by the grace of God the true Faith Catholike and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolique, from the which I have through my fault gone astray, and separated my selfe since, &amp;c. and desirous to returne to the flocke of Christs true Sheep-fold, which is the Catholique, Apostolique, and Romish Church, confesse to have Abjured and cursed all the errours and heresie of the <hi>Lutherans, Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinists,</hi> and <hi>Hugonots,</hi> and all other Heresie whatsoever, where-with I have heretofore beene defamed or touched: And I agree to the Faith of our holy mother the Church, and desire you in the name of God, of His Sonne Jesus Christ, and of the glorious Virgin His Mother <hi>Mary,</hi> and of all the Saints of Paradice,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:36221:84"/>that it would please you to receive me into the flock and Sheepfold of Gods people, which live under the obedience of the <hi>Pope,</hi> ordained our Saviour Jesus Christs Vicat in the said Church, submitting my selfe patiently to abide, and willingly to do the Penance which it shal please you to enjoyne me for the absolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my faults committed, whilst I was in the fore-said Sects, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I aske and require pardon of God, and of his said Church, and of you (that be appointed my Pastors by God the Creator) absolution, with such penance as you shall judge to be wholesome for the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of my sins and offences. And to the intent you should know that I have and do make this Abju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from my heart. I confesse moreover before God and you, that I beleeve that which is contained in the Symbole or Creed of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, and <hi>Athanasius,</hi> and other Confessions of Faith made and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by the whole Councels of
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:36221:85"/>the Catholique, Apostolique, and <hi>Romish</hi> Church, that is, I beleeve in one only God, the Father Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Creator of Heaven and Earth, and of all things visible and invisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and in one Lord, our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, the only Son engendred by God the Father before the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution of the world, God of God, Light of Light, true God of true God, engendred not Created, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>substantiall with the Father, by whom all things were made, who for us men, and for our salvation, descended from Heaven, &amp;c. <hi>as in the Beliefe of Morning Prayer.</hi> I beleeve likewise, acknowledge and confesse all that which is contained in the Bookes, as well of the old, as of the new Testament, approved by the said Holy and Apostolique Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> according to the sense and interpretation of the holy Doctors received by the same, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting all other interpretation as false and erroneous. I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the seven Sacraments of the
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:36221:85"/>said Catholike, Apostolike and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish Church, that they were insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted by our Lord Jesus Christ, and that they be necessary for the salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mankind, although that all of them are not of necessity to be conferred to all, that is to say, I confesse that the said seven Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are these, <hi>Baptisme, Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, Eucharist,</hi> which is the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Altar, <hi>Penance, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame Ʋnction, Order,</hi> and <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage,</hi> and that the said Sacraments confer grace, and that of them, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme, Confirmation, and Order, cannot be reiterated without sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege. That the said Sacraments have the effect which the said Church teacheth, &amp; that the forme &amp; usage wherewith they bee ministred to Christians, is holy and necessary. I acknowledge also that the holy Masse is a sacrifice and oblation of the very body and bloud of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Jesus Christ, under the forme of bread and wine mingled with water, which substances of bread
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:36221:86"/>and wine under the said formes (are in the Masse by the words w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> serve for consecration, said and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by the Priest) transubstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated and transformed into the substance of the said body &amp; bloud of Jesus Christ. Notwithstanding, that the qualities and accidents re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in the said formes after the said consecration, &amp; that the Masse is holesome and profitable as well for the quick as the dead. I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and confesse the concomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, that is to say, that in receiving the body of Jesus Christ under the forme of bread alone, I likewise re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the bloud of Jesus Christ. I confesse that Prayer and intercessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Saints for the quicke and the dead is holy, good and healthful for Christians, and is not contrary (for any respect) to the glory of God. That prayers made in the Church for the faithfull which are dead, do profit them for the remission of their sinnes, and lessening of their paines incurred for the same. That
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:36221:86"/>there is a Purgatory where the souls abiding are succoured by the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the faithfull. I confesse that we must honour and call upon the Saints which reigne with Jesus Christ, and that they make inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession for us to God, and that their Relikes are to be worshipped. That the Commandements and Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Catholique, Apostolique and Romish Church, as well they which pertaine to the forme &amp; ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of divine Service, and to assist the same, which I think be to draw Christian people to piety and turning to their God, as fasting, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staining from meats, observation of Holy-dayes, and Ecclesiasticall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie, according to the tradition of the Apostles and holy Fathers, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued since the Primitive Church till this time, &amp; afterwards brought into the Church by the ordinances of Councels received in the same of long and ancient time, or of late, be good and holy, to the which I will and ought to obey, as prescribed and
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:36221:87"/>appointed by the Holy Ghost, the Author and director of that which serveth for the keeping of Christian Religion, and of the Catholique A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postolique and <hi>Roman</hi> Church. I Beleeve also and accept all the arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of originall sin, and of Justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. I affirme assuredly, that we ought to have and keep the Images of Jesus Christ, of his holy Mother, and all other Saints, and do honour and reverence unto them. I confesse the power of Indulgence and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons to be left in the Church by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, and the use of them to be very healthfull, as also I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and confesse the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be the Mother and chiefe of all Churches, and conducted by the Holy Ghost: and that other pretended particular inspirations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the same, come of the sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gestion of the Devill, the Prince of dissention, which would separate the union of the mysticall Body of the Saviour of the world. Finally, I promise straightly to keep all that
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:36221:87"/>was ordained at the last Generall Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> and promise to God and you, never more to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the Catholique, Aposto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, and <hi>Roman</hi> Church: and if I do (which God forbid) I submit my selfe to the penalties of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of the said Church, made, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, and appointed against them which fall back into Apostasie. The which Abjuration and Confession I have subscribed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>THE KINGS LETTER to <hi>M. de Guise,</hi> and other Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants and Governours of his Provinces, by the which hee wholly abolisheth and subvert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all the Edicts of Pacifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and willeth that only the <hi>Romish</hi> Religion should take place in his Realme.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE King knowing that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration which hee made upon the occasion which lately chanced in the City of</hi> Paris, <hi>the remembrances
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:36221:88"/>and instructions of his will which he sent round about to all Governours of his Provinces, and Lieutenants generall therein, and particular let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to the Seneshals, and his Courts of Parliament, and other Officers and Ministers of Justice, cannot hitherto stay the course of murthers and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries done in the most part of the Cities of this Realme, to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties great displeasure: hath advised for a more singular remedy, to send all the said Governours into every of their charges and governments, assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring himselfe, that according to the quality and power which they have of his Majesty, they can well follow and observe his intent, the which more fully to declare, his Majesty hath caused his Letters Patents to be dispatched, which shall be delivered them. Besides the contents whereof</hi> M. de Guise <hi>the Governour, and Lieutenant generall for his Majesty in</hi> Champaigne <hi>and</hi> Brye, <hi>shall call before him the Gentlemen of the new</hi> Religion <hi>abiding within his govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:36221:88"/>and shall tell them that the Kings will and intent is to preserve them, their wives, children and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, and to maintain them in pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session of their goods, so that on their part they live quietly, and render to his Majesty obedience and fidelity as they ought: in which doing the King also will defend them, that they shall not be molestea or troubled by way of Justice, or otherwise in their persons and goods, by reason of things done during the troubles, and before the Edict of Pacification of August,</hi> 1570. <hi>And afterwards hee shall lovingly admonish them to continue no longer in the Error of the new O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, and to returne to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Religion, reconciling themselves to the Catholique Romish Church, under the doctrine and obedience whereof, the King his predecessours and their subjects have alwayes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily lived, and this Realme hath been carefully conducted and maintained: Shewing to them the mischiefes and calamities which have happened in
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:36221:89"/>this Realme, since these new opinions have entred into mens spirits: How many murders have been caused by such which have fallen from the right way holden by their Ancestors. First, they made them separate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves from the Church, then from their next of kindred, and also to be estranged from the service of their King, as a man may see since his reigne. And although the authors and heads of that side, would have covered their doings under the title of</hi> Religion <hi>and conscience: yet their deeds and workes have shewen well enough that the name of</hi> Religion <hi>was but a</hi> vizzard <hi>to cover their drifts and disobedience, and under that pretence to assemble and suborn people, and to make and compell them to sweare in the cause under the title of disobedience, and by such wayes to turne them from the naturall affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction which they owe to the King, and consequently from his obedience; it being notorious, that what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement soever the King could
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:36221:89"/>make to them of the new</hi> Religion, <hi>they have not since his reigne obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him otherwise than pleased their heads. And contrariwise, when their said heads commanded them to arise and take to their weapons, to set up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Cities, to burne Churches, to sack and pill, to trouble the Realme, and fill it with bloud and fire, they which went so astray to follow them, forgot all trust and duty of good subjects, to execute and obey their comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements. Which things if the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen will well consider, they shall easily judge how unhappy and mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable their condition shall be, if they continue longer therein. For they may well thinke of themselves, that the King being taught by experience of so great a danger, from the which it hath pleased God to preserve him and his Estate, and having proved the mischiefes and calamities which this Realm hath suffred by the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise of the heads of this cause, their adherents and complices, that he will never willingly be served with any
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:36221:90"/>Gentlemen of his subjects that be of any other Religion than the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, in the which also the King, following his predecessors, will live and die. He willeth also to take away all mistrust amongst his subjects, and to quench the rising of discords and seditions, that all they of whom he is served in honourable places, and specially the Gentlemen which desire to be accompted his good and lawfull subjects, and would obtaine his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and be employed in charges of his service, according to their degrees and qualities, doe make profession here-after to live in the same Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion that he doth: having tryed that discords and civill warres will not cease in a State where there be many Religions, and that it is not possible for a king to maintain in his Realme diversities in Religion, but that hee shal lose the good wil &amp; benevolēce of his subjects, yea, and they which are of a contrary Religion to his, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire nothing in their heart more than the change of the King and of his
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:36221:90"/>Estate. For the reason above-said, the Duke of</hi> Guise, <hi>to bring the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to this passe, shall take paines to perswade the Nobility and others in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the said new</hi> Opinion, <hi>to returne of themselves, and of their owne free-will to the Catholique Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and to abjure and renounce the</hi> New, <hi>without any more expresse commandement from the King. For howsoever it be, his Majesty is resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to make his subjects live in his Religion, and never to suffer what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever may betide, that there shall bee any other forme or exercise of</hi> Religion <hi>in his Realm then the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique; The said Duke of</hi> Guise <hi>shall communicate with the principal Officers and Magistrates, having the principall charge and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration of Justice in Cities of his government, his Majesties declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to the intent they should know his mind, and the good end where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto he tendeth for the uniting and quietnesse of his subjects, to the intent the said</hi> M. de Guise, <hi>and the said
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:36221:91"/>Officers and Magistrates, should with one concord, intelligence and correspondence proceed to the effect above-said, so that fruit and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse may thereof ensue, such as his Majesty desireth, not only for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, but for the whole Realme. The Baylifes and Stewards which are not in Religion accordingly qualified, shall within one moneth resigne their Offices to Gentlemen capable, and of the quality required by the Edict, which may keepe and exercise the same. And to the intent this should be done, his Majesty doth now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently declare them deprived after the said month, if they do not then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe, that they shall have no occasion or colour of excuse to delay their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signations, and yet permitteth them in the mean while to resigne without any fine paying. All Baylifes and Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards shall be resident at their offices upon paine of losse of the same, and if they cannot so be, then they shall be bound to resigne. All Archbishops and Bishops shall likewise be resident
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:36221:91"/>in their Dioces and such as for age &amp; other indisposition of person cannot preach the Word of God, nor edifie the people, and do other functions ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to their charge and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, shall be bound to take a conductor to comfort them, and to employ them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to the duty of their charge. To the which Conductor they shall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point an honest and reasonable pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion according to the fruits and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue of their living. Also Parsons and Vicars shall be resident at their Benefices, or else shall be admonished to resigne them to such as will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sident, and do their duty. Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops and Bishops shall take infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of them which hold Abbeyes, Priories, and other Benefices in their Diocesse, of what quality so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they are, and how they do their duty in the administration of them, where upon they shall make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse by word unto the Governours, which shall send them to the King to provide therein as reason shall move him. They shall compell the Curates
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:36221:92"/>actually to abide at the places of their Benefices, or else shall appoint other in their steads according to the dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition of the Cannons.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>At</hi> Paris <date>
                     <hi>the third of November,</hi> 1572.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Signed</hi> CHARLES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>LETTERS OF <hi>M. DE Gordes,</hi> the Kings Lieutenant in <hi>Daulphine,</hi> to certaine of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> in his Government, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he exhorteth them to come backe againe to the Religion of <hi>Rome;</hi> and how the King is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to suffer none other.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>SIr, I am sufficiently advertised of your behaviour, but you should remember what advertisements I have before sent you to returne to the Catholique Religion of your selfe, which is the best hold and stay that you can choose for your preservation and health putting from you all those which perswade you to the contrary, who would abide to see any commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or disorder, rather than abate
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:36221:92"/>any point of their opinion. And by this meanes you shall make evident to the King, the will which you say you have to obey his Majesty, counselling you for as much as I desire your well doing, that this is the best for you to do, without looking for any more open commandement: otherwise assure your selfe, there can but evill come of it, and that his Majesty would be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed. And thus I pray God to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vise you, and give you hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> holy grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From</hi> Grenoble <date>
                     <hi>the sixt of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> 1572.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your entire good friend, <hi>GORDES.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <head>THE ANSWER OF THE Gentlemen, Captaines, Burges<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and other being in the Town of <hi>Rochell,</hi> to the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that have been given them in the name of the King, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive garrisons.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>WE the Gentlemen, Captaines, Burgesses, and other now being in this Towne of</hi> Rochell, <hi>doe give
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:36221:93"/>answer to you</hi> Mounsieur N. <hi>and to such commandements as you give us in the name of his Majesty, that we cannot acknowledge that, that which is signified unto us, and the Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation which you require that wee should cause to bee published, doe proceed from his Majesty. And thereof we call to witnesse his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty himselfe, his Letters of the</hi> 22. <hi>and</hi> 24. <hi>of August, his owne signet, and the publishing of the same Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, by the which his said Majesty layeth all the fault of all the trouble lately hapned, &amp; of the cruel slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter done at</hi> Paris, <hi>upon those of the house of</hi> Guise, <hi>protesting that hee had enough to do to keepe himselfe safe within his Castell of</hi> Louure <hi>with those of his Guard. And we shal never suffer our selves to be perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that so foule an enterprise and so barbarous a slaughter hath at any time entred into the mind of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, much lesse that the same hath been done by his expresse commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as the paper importeth which
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:36221:93"/>you have exhibited unto us, nor that his Majesty hath been so ill advised, as himself to cut off his own armes, or to defile the sacred wedding of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame his own sister with the shedding of so much</hi> noble &amp; innocent bloud, <hi>and with the shame of so cruell a fact to stain the nation of</hi> France <hi>and the bloud royall, which hath heretofore ever among al nations born the name of</hi> franke <hi>and</hi> courteous: <hi>nor that he hath had mind to deliver matter to writers to set forth a tragical history such as antiquity hath never heard speake of the like, and such as posteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty cannot report without horror. But that it was first layd at</hi> Rome, <hi>and afterward hatched at</hi> Paris, <hi>by the authors of all the troubles of</hi> France. <hi>And howsoever it be, we are ready to maintaine that out of the mouth of his Majesty doth not proceed hot and cold, white and blacke, and that hee doth not now say one thing, and by and by another, as hee should doe if the paper that you present unto us had passed from him, protesting
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:36221:94"/>that he will inviolably keepe his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, and immediately breaking the same in declaring that he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded those murders to be committed, having also made protestation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that it is to his great griefe, and done by the outrage and violence of those of</hi> Guise, <hi>against whom he was not able to make speedy resistance in time, as his Majesty desired. And in this quarrell, wee the Gentlemen, Captaines, and other that make you this answer, are ready to try it by combate man to man, or otherwise, to maintain the honour of our King a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all those that so prophane holy things, and as much as in them lyeth do by such words and titles villai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nously defile the excellence of his Majesty, and of the noble Princes of his bloud. Which we may right well conjecture &amp; estimate, by the slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that are yet in doing, as well in the Town of</hi> Paris, <hi>as else-where, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on so many Noblemen, Gentlemen and other, men, women and children, and upon a great number of young
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:36221:94"/>schollars (the maintenance under God, of Realmes and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weales in time to come) and by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other barbarous, unnaturall and unmanly acts generally committed. We thinke therefore and judge that herein treason is enterprised against the person of his Majesty, and of my Lords his brethren, and that the</hi> Guisians <hi>mean to invade the Crown of the Realme, as they have of long time practised, and howsoever it be, we say that his Majesty is forced by the power that they have taken upon them, and usurped, by meanes of the rebellious stirre of the Commons of</hi> Paris. <hi>As for that which they say, that the Admirall and those of the</hi> Religion <hi>had conspired against the Kings Majesty and his brethren; these bee allegations of as great truth, and of as good likelihood, as their manner of proceeding in justice hath been orderly, beginning at exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution before examination of the fact. But it is now no need to tarry
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:36221:95"/>for time to discover it, for the matter is plaine to be seene with eye, and groaped with hand, and all those of the Romish Religion that have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining any drop of nature of man, doe confesse it and hold downe their heads for shame, cursing both with heart and mouth the cruell execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of this abominable enterprise, and the wicked disturbers of common quiet, which can yet no more suffer, than they hitherto have done, that this poore Realme should long enjoy the benefit of that peace, which the King alone, next under God, had wisely caused to be made, and to be accordingly observed, whereof this Realme began to feele the good taste, to the great contentment of all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, except the enemies of peace and of this Realme, namely, the</hi> Guisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. <hi>Finally, when his Majesty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of their hands and power, shall declare what is his pleasure, we will endevour us to obey him in all things, wherein our consciences,
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:36221:95"/>which are dedicate to God alone, shal not be wounded,</hi>
               <note place="margin">a true christian resolution</note>
               <hi>in which case wee will rather forsake the earth than heaven, and our fraile and transito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry houses rather than the heavenly mansions. But hitherto the law of Nature, and the duty that we owe to our naturall Prince, to the preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his Crowne, and to the safety of our lives, our wives and children, doth command us to stand upon our guard, and not to put to our selves in the mercy of those that have received the same bloudy commission from the</hi> Guisians, <hi>under the preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded name of the King to use us in the same manner as they have wickedly, trayterously, and unnaturally done to those about his Majesty, and as it were under his wings, and under the skirts of his robe, which the traytors</hi> strangers <hi>have stained with the true</hi> French <hi>bloud, without that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty hath been able to remedy it, nor to stay their cursed attempts: so much lesse is he able now so farre off
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:36221:96"/>to defend us as he would, which his Majesties good will being knowne unto us, doth arme us for our defence, and for the safeguard of our lives, and for the priviledges which he hath given us, untill such time as he shall be able by himselfe to defend us against his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and ours.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>IN the Epist. page</hi> 2. <hi>line.</hi> 13. <hi>for</hi> deceit <hi>read</hi> deceive. <hi>p.</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>put out</hi> (it)</p>
            <p>Pag. 11. <hi>lin.</hi> 3. <hi>for</hi> Princes <hi>read</hi> Prince. <hi>p.</hi> 31. <hi>l</hi> 7. Margrat <hi>r.</hi> Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. <hi>p.</hi> 35. <hi>lin.</hi> 9. <hi>for</hi> sealed <hi>r.</hi> seale. <hi>p.</hi> 53. <hi>l</hi> 5. <hi>for</hi> County <hi>r.</hi> Count. <hi>p.</hi> 59. <hi>l.</hi> 17. <hi>for</hi> County <hi>r.</hi> Count. <hi>p.</hi> 66. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>for</hi> keeker <hi>r.</hi> keeper. <hi>p.</hi> 78. <hi>l.</hi> 22. <hi>for</hi> fiances <hi>r.</hi> finances. <hi>p.</hi> 81. <hi>l.</hi> 25. <hi>for</hi> Majesty <hi>r.</hi> Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties. <hi>p.</hi> 84. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>for</hi> speeces <hi>r.</hi> speeches. <hi>p.</hi> 90. <hi>l.</hi> 15. <hi>for</hi> that <hi>Parisians r.</hi> that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risians <hi>p.</hi> 105. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>for</hi> Cod <hi>r.</hi> God. <hi>p.</hi> 129. <hi>l.</hi> 14. <hi>for</hi> house <hi>r.</hi> houses. <hi>p.</hi> 157. <hi>l.</hi> 11. <hi>for</hi> way <hi>r.</hi> away.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:36221:96"/>
            <p>ORdered by the Committee for Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that this Booke entituled <hi>A French Massacre,</hi> or <hi>Patterne of popish Peace,</hi> be re-printed; and that Master <hi>Thomas Case</hi> be desired to nominate the man that shall print it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Iohn White.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="nomination">
            <p>I Nominate <hi>Richard Whitaker</hi> to Print this Booke, as is desired by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee for printing.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Case.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>